<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the honor of Gods house: or, The true paterne of the Church, shewed in the parts and pietie of it with a discovery of the true cause and cure of our present contentions, and an answer of such objections as may offend the weake.</title>
            <author>Yates, John, d. ca. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26089</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120542</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855738</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855738</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15828)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1056:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the honor of Gods house: or, The true paterne of the Church, shewed in the parts and pietie of it with a discovery of the true cause and cure of our present contentions, and an answer of such objections as may offend the weake.</title>
                  <author>Yates, John, d. ca. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 28, 33-70, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] C[otes] for William Cooke, and are to be sold at his shop neere Furnivalls Inne Gate in Holbourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Yates, i.e. John Yates (d. ca. 1660), but possibly by another John Yates.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21240:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE HONOR OF GODS HOVSE:</p>
            <p>OR, THE TRVE PATERNE Of the Church, ſhewed in the parts And pietie of it;</p>
            <p>With a Diſcovery of the true Cauſe and Cure Of our preſent Contentions,</p>
            <p>And an anſwer of ſuch Objections as may Offend the weake.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>CANT. 6.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Returne, returne, O, Shulamite, returne returne that we may behold thee; what ſhall you ſee in the Shulamite, but as the company of an Army.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>William Cooke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop neere <hi>Furnivalls</hi> Inne Gate in <hi>Holbourne.</hi> 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:21240:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Perlegi hunc tractatum, cui titulus eſt</hi> (A Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the honour of God Houſe, <hi>&amp;c) in quo nihil reperio ſanae doctrinae aut bonis moribut contrarium, quo minus imprimatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex Aedibus Lambeth.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jun.</hi> 15. 1637.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>IOHN OLIVER <hi>Reveren. in Ch. Patri &amp; Dom. Dom. Ar. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant. Sacell. Dom.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21240:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL CLERE TALBOT, D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> of Law, Comiſſary to the Reverend Father in God, the <hi>L. Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> one of his MAIESTIES <hi>Iuſtices of Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am forced to ſet forth my ſelfe as well as my Sermon, and to ſatiſfie ſome. I muſt tell them as well what I am, as what I have ſaid. A ſhort Sermon is often the occaſion of much diſcourſe, and many
<pb facs="tcp:21240:3"/>like the <hi>Athenians</hi> delight in nothing but to heare and tell newes, and ſome like the devill are not ſo idle, as ill occupied in ſlandering of others. The biting of mad dogges admits of medicine to helpe it, but there is no Phyſitian that knowes a remedy againſt a ſlander. All the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, that <hi>Mala opinio benè parta delectat,</hi> a mans owne conſcience may be his cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: <hi>Vnus mihi pro populo erit,</hi> one underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding man is better than a multitude, whoſe very wiſedome (as the Wiſeman ſaith) is to be deſpiſed, <hi>Omnis honeſtae reima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus judex eſt vulgus,</hi> the common people are corrupt judges, <hi>Eadem probamus, eadem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendimus, hic eſt exitus omnis judicij in quo lis ſecundum plures datur,</hi> in number of voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there is no certaintie of truth, <hi>ſatis eſt unus, ſatis eſt nullus,</hi> one or none may be ſufficient to ſatisfie in a good cauſe, which as I am perſwaded I have undertaken. I am not aſhamed to paſſe it from the Pulpit to the Preſſe, and to Print what I preached. In both I have your requeſt, and it is ſome
<pb facs="tcp:21240:3"/>part of a requitall to ſay, <hi>Hoc ego non multis ſed tibi,</hi> I owe as much as you have deſired, and will not be dainty by your hands to deliver it to others. That you have found the approbation you ſought for, is to mee a ſecond confirmation, it may doe more good than I expected: I ſhall be glad to helpe the weakeſt, and not to receive him for controverſies of diſputations. I have not ſtirred the ſtone they ſtumble upon, nor moved their mindes with noveltie, <hi>Qui intempestivè monet ille nocet,</hi> a monition muſt be as a medicine ſeaſonably applied. When there is no motion of humours in a body, their very agitation is dangerous, and no pacification to be expected by their purgation; but the Aphoriſme is true, when they move remove them, leaſt they doe miſchiefe, <hi>Si quid movendum move humores, qui turgent purgentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Me thinkes our diſeaſes are diſcovered by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the right method, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Many are unruly, vaine talkers, deceivers.</hi> Authoritie is diſobeyed. Secondly, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
<pb facs="tcp:21240:4"/>is defended. Thirdly, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence deceives others. Theſe diſeaſes are apparent in many, whoſe malady is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention with their Superiours, which they defend by bookes, and by the ſame, poyſon moſt of the people, who looke not ſo much into the cauſe as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and complying in affection with the Authors, loſe the apprehenſion of the truth, which whoſoever ſhall reveale it to them, ſhall not be heard for the prejudice they have conceived. <hi>Prava dogmata,</hi> wicked doctrines make Heretickes and poiſon their mindes: but <hi>diverſa ſtudia,</hi> ſmall differences will make Schiſmatickes, and ſet them out of good thoughts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all they cannot affect. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> diſputes the caſe charitably, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10.19. he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves it in part, and paſſeth not the ſame ſentence upon all, and mitigates the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter further by an effectuall gradation from Schiſme to hereſie, as from the leſſe to the greater. No marvell you are divided in Rites and Ceremonies, and contrary
<pb facs="tcp:21240:4"/>Cuſtomes, wherein wee for our parts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not, neither the Churches of God; but ſtudy peace and quiet, as counting them no matters of moment to cauſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. Such contentious ſpirits make Gods people come together, <hi>not for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but for the worſe,</hi> where is the fault? not in the Church, but the bad humours of it, in ſuch as are in the Church, but not of it, in ſuch as have leaſt to doe with it, yet make worke enough for them which have moſt to doe, and ſet all into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion. I ſay the holy Apoſtle helpes the ſtaggering Chriſtian, and labours to make him ſtand upright.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I beleeve it to be in your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and onely of thoſe that will not be of you. Secondly, it is from a bad cauſe to a good end. The devill moves it, but God will have the glory of it, and you ſhall have the good, in being approved to him. Secondly, in being made manifeſt to others, and that firſt, that you are not the Schiſmatickes: ſecondly, that you are
<pb facs="tcp:21240:5"/>ſuch as the Church approves: thirdly, you neede not wonder at Schiſmes, when Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan can raiſe hereſies. Thats a happy Church that is without weedes, and a thouſand ſeparations are not to be truſted, that ſeek ſafety where Satan ſhall not find them; <hi>America</hi> is no more the place than <hi>Rome,</hi> Satan is to be feared hath found and will finde their ſocieties, but I will not accuſe them ſo much as defend my ſelfe, and tell all men what I am, ſure I ſhould be, if I be righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>I am <hi>unus in corpore,</hi> as well as <hi>unus in capite,</hi> one that ſtrives as much for one Church as for one Chriſt, and as it is my duty to name my ſelfe a Chriſtian from my communion with Chriſt, ſo ſhall it ever be the ſame to ſirname my ſelfe a Catholike from my communion with his body. Seeing you have drawne me out to ſay ſome thing, I ſay it for the Church, and ſeeke pacification of that which is now in agitation; and becauſe the Altar
<pb facs="tcp:21240:5"/>breedes the greateſt quarrell, I will firſt labour to take away the offence in the name; ſecondly, I will examine whether every Altar induceth a ſacrifice; thirdly, whether the ſacrifice ſuperinduceth the ſinne of Idolatry; fourthly, I will ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſeverall inſtances of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Gods Houſe to bring us in love with it; fiftly, give directions to avoid danger; and this I am forced to fixe before my Sermon to make it more acceptable in the reading. I know it is not all one to Preach in a Pulpit, and ſpeake out of a Preſſe, my deſire is to make way by a Preface, that no prejudice may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in a ſhort Sermon, to ſay it was Preached indeede, but nothing proved. I am to take my leave of you, and know not whether I ſhall give you thankes for that you have brought me upon the ſtage, or ſay I ſhould have thanked you more to have buried all this in my ſtudy. Your thankes and mine are to be alike. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb facs="tcp:21240:6"/>I will thinke you meant me well, and for that I thanke you, and reſt, and remaine.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to be Commanded <hi>IOHN YATES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:21240:6"/>
            <head>The danger of an Altar in the name and uſe, the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of it in ſtanding before God, and directions how it ought not to ſtand before Idols.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2. <hi>King</hi> 16.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Altar of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> removes the Altar of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Myſterium ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitatis.</hi> Act. 17.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Cor. 10.20.22. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Tim. 4.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſe Texts have all one meaning, and the myſtery is this in the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall, office</hi> and <hi>worſhip.</hi> Their Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>celebre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> viri defuncti,</hi> they are the beſt of dead men. Their Office, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God &amp; men. Their Wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip. Acts 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ver. 24. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ver. 23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ibid.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Cor. 10 20. Temples, Altars, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Sacrifices. ver. 22. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are as much as Sacrifice &amp; Altar. St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the <hi>Athenians</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of dead Mediators, to which he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth Chriſt as the living and ſole Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, which to them was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Act. 17.18. 1 Cor. 8.5, 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. One Lord to mediate to one God, and many Lords to mediate to many Gods, the two maine myſteries in the world.</note> and the <hi>Syrian</hi> gods the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> As it is Gods grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt honour, to have his owne Table or Altar to ſtand before him, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 16.14. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 41.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.13. So is it his greateſt diſhonour to have either ſtand before an Idoll. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 16.14, 15. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.23. We will doe our beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to deliver you from the danger, by determining the dignity of an Altar before God, where no Idoll inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes, but God immediately is worſhipped in it, or before it. It is no humane invention to place a Table or Altar im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before God, as is cleare, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 41.22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.13. There is no difference betweene the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord, and the Table of dead men, but that they in their pictures and perſons come betweene him and us in our worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 17. well conſidered, will declare the whole myſtery in this forme. Firſt, an Altar, which if it were to a knowne God, and that according to his Will were no ſin, but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding honour done unto him: but there be two things more that make all this moſt abhominable, and like the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> Firſt, a viſible Idoll, called σέβασμα, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.23. Secondly, an inviſible Diety, called δαιμόνιον <hi>v.</hi> 18. To ſpeake plainely, there is above the Altar an Image to be worſhipped, and the Soule of a dead man conceived to be in that Image to heare our prayers, receive our offerings, and to mediate for us with Almighty God, theſe two things
<pb facs="tcp:21240:7"/>are the great abhominations that the Scriptures detect, and diſcover unto us, to incite our deteſtation: theſe things wee teach not the people, but take occaſion in our ignorance to wrong God in his worſhip, and ſay, the Table is an Idoll, and we worſhip it; and ſo being ſtarke blind in the great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of iniquity make that an Idoll, which never Pagan, nor Papiſt, nor any man in his right wits ever imagined ſo to be.</p>
            <p>The Idoll is either the viſible image above the Altar, or the inviſible and falſe Deity in the image, which to worſhip is Idolatry: but remove theſe two, in which is all the danger, and ſuffer God immediately to come in with the Altar, and then proſtration before it is without danger, becauſe it muſt needs be to God, and no Idoll; except you will make it one, which as yet was never imagined by God or man: And ſhall we be the firſt to find it out, to trouble the Church in a needleſſe diſputation, that none will raiſe, but a meere <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus</hi> in that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. calls διδασκαλί<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>α<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> δαιμονίων, interpreted by <hi>Epiphanius</hi> thus, μύθους τῶν νεκρῶν, <hi>fables of the dead,</hi> and delivers it in the example of <hi>Baal,</hi> whoſe ſacrifices and ceremonies the Scriptures deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to be done to the dead. <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.28. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.1. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.28. But I will anſwer to that which they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in ſeverall particulars.</p>
            <div type="danger">
               <head>1. Danger; an Altar is ſcandalous in the name.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezech.</hi> 44.16. The Table or Altar ſhews who are nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt God, and freeſt from I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.23, 24. <hi>Donum offerre, &amp; ad Altare afferre ſine charitate, non eſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um, impium eſt accedere ad merſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſine fraterna c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aritate. Ergo corſilium Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti eſt generale et quod vis Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare ſignifieat, ſive I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>daeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, five Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</hi>
                  </note> 41.22. <hi>This Altar is the Table before the Lord.</hi> Mal. 1.7. <hi>You have polluted mine Altar, in that you ſay my Table is contemptible.</hi> ver. 12. <hi>The Table of the Lord is polluted.</hi> Both places ſhew that the Holy Ghoſt is not ſo curious, as theſe men are captious; to call an Altar a
<pb facs="tcp:21240:7"/>Table, and a Table an Altar; and for ought I know, in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to our times, we have an Altar of Incenſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.3 and of that ſpeaks <hi>Ezechi.</hi> and compared with <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.2. it exceeds the Legall Altar a Cubit in the hight, and a cub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the length. This Prophet miſtakes not his meaſure, but ſhews the myſtery and meaning to be in the times of the augmentation of grace, and ſo <hi>Malachy</hi> applies it to the Gentiles, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.11.</p>
               <p>It would be obſerved that of the two Altars, the Altar of prayers is applyed to vs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.3. and it is that at which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtands, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>He ſtood by the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar;</hi> that muſt be by the ſence that ſome give, <hi>At himſelfe, Rev.</hi> 9.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Altar before God:</hi> That is, if we beleeve our former Expoſitors, <hi>God before God.</hi> If this Expoſition diſpleaſe, as it muſt, then take and try this of mine, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. <hi>Breaking of bread and prayers,</hi> are joyned together; where wee breake bread, and pray, there <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> ſtands, that is, by his holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or Altar; where we doe both, and may doe them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence to any that will not be willfull in wayes by themſelves.</p>
               <div type="exposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Expoſition of τὸ ἱερὸν, and κατ' ὀῖκον,</hi> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 2.46.</bibl>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is neceſſary we expound the good example of the firſt Chriſtians; and becauſe we ſpeake ſo much of their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, it would be knowne where it firſt ſtood, and in what manner it was placed. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.46. tells us of the Temple, or holy place frequented by Chriſtians: but there their Altar would not be admitted, or their breaking of bread permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Now it was neceſſary that Chriſtians ſhould receive the Lords Supper, and breake their Sacramentall bread with holy prayers and ſervices meet for ſuch a Myſtery: where this was done, the ſame Text teacheth, that it was κατ' ὀῖκον, <hi>Secundùm domum,</hi> which phraſe well underſtood
<pb facs="tcp:21240:8"/>will helpe much to know what holy places Chriſtians held beſide the Temple.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Coloſ</hi> 4.15. <hi>Philem.</hi> ver. 2. Ἐκκλησία κατ' ὀῖκον, its the locall deſcription of the Church, and all laid together, makes us underſtand the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why bread muſt be broken out of the Temple, when the Chriſtians were dayly in it ſerving God. No man needs to doubt of it, that it was becauſe the Temple received no ſuch ſacrifice as Chriſtians were bound to offer, nor ſuch an Altar or Table as ſerved for that uſe. And here we muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, whether the place were common, or conſecrate; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> reſolves us, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20, 21, 22. <hi>When ye come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether therefore into one place, this is not to eate the Lords Supper, &amp;c. Have yee not houſes</hi> for common eating and drinking, &amp;c. <hi>Deſpiſe yee the Church of God?</hi> A man may deſpiſe the place as well as the people, and by irreverence ſhame himſelfe as well as others in his behaviour. Women, when they worſhip, muſt remember that where they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the Angels give their attendance, and for prefence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake muſt preſent themſelves in a ſeemely manner.</p>
                  <p>Seeing it muſt be κατ' ὀῖκον, that cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ν τῷ ἱερῶ, I would demand whether in ſo holy a ſervice, as receiving the holy Sacrament, that which is κατ' ὀῖκον, ought not to be ῶ̔ς <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ν τῷ ἱερῶ, that what is done at any <hi>houſe</hi> in this kind, ought it not to be done as in a ſacred place? My reſolution is, it muſt; and that Board where wee receiue ſo holy a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that place where ſo holy a Board doth ſtand, ought to have no other imployment.</p>
                  <p>The firſt Chriſtian Church amongſt the Gentiles was in <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> and began in <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Captaines houſe, and had that good ſucceſſe, that when St. <hi>Paul</hi> landed there, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.22. hee found the Church aſſembled in an upper roome; not as <hi>Beza</hi> makes bold to interprete, <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> came downe to</hi> Ceſarea, <hi>and went up to</hi> Ieruſalem, &amp;c. but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, is. He aſcended, and ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:21240:8"/>the Church in <hi>Ceſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a.</hi> When <hi>Iudea</hi> was the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-houſe to perſecute Chriſtians, <hi>Ceſarea</hi> was their San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary to deliver them. A good <hi>Cornelius</hi> converted, is a Captaine to Chriſtians, and commands them peace where he hath power to rule. At <hi>Epheſus</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> procures the <hi>Schoole of</hi> Tyrannus, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.9, 10. and for the ſpace of two yeeres makes it his chaire of Doctrine, and place of Gods ſervice. <hi>Tyranuus</hi> to me is no Schoole-maſter to teach prophane Arts, where St. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth Divinity; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Tyrannus</hi> was the <hi>Doner</hi> or giver of the place, which being void, is peaceably poſſeſſed of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians for holy uſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 28.20.30, 31. St. <hi>Pauls</hi> hired houſe was an holy place for the Word and Sacraments. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> hire their houſe, and fit the faireſt roome for the Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Being baniſhed from <hi>Rome, Acts</hi> 18.2. they are left of St. <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> where they doe the like, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Nymphas</hi> does the like at <hi>Laodicea, Coloſ.</hi> 4.15. and ſo does <hi>Philemon ver.</hi> 2. For the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> and <hi>Archippus</hi> their Paſtor lives in his houſe. It is ſaid of <hi>Gaius, Rom.</hi> 16.23. that he was <hi>Hoſpes ſancti Pauli, &amp; totius Eccleſiae,</hi> That hee found St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the whole Church houſe and hatbour. I hope all this will yeeld ſome helpe to explaine what is meant by meeting, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a holy convention of the Saints to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the holy Sacrament, and ſet a part both place and Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for ſo holy an uſe.</p>
                  <p>Our Saviour, <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.12. ſhewes foure things in the place where he ſupped before his death: Firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a place elevated from the earth, and it is Saint <hi>Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ianz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns</hi> note, that the very place teacheth us with what thoughts we ought to come to the holy Sacrament. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, great and ſpacious for uſe and ſervice. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, trimmed and beautified. Fourthly, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, furniſhed and prepared with all neceſſary Vtenſils, &amp;c. Such
<pb facs="tcp:21240:9"/>places had Chriſtians; and as they neglected not the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, whiles they might enjoy it: ſo it pleaſed God in the end to give them <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſtately Temples to ſerve God in, and therein <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> like another <hi>Salomon,</hi> was appointed of God to enlarge the ſtraitned limits of poore perſecuted Chriſtians. I will adde to their breaking of bread that which alſo went with it, their breaking of bread to the brethren. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.16. Thus did Chriſtians converſe and come together in the primative times, and did all things <hi>with gladneſſe and ſingleneſſe of heart.</hi> Would God their patterne of piety might paſſe in our dayes, and that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, with one accord in the Temple God were worſhipped of us: But alas, we muſt doe it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, when nothing foreeth us thereunto. Our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are open, Tables prepared, and we fling away, and fly to Conventicles, where I hope to ſhew, nothing can be done lawfully by thoſe that leave us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proof">
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18.21.</bibl>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>Our ſecond proofe is the New Teſtament, and it lyes in comparing Altar with Altar, and Table with Table; for ſo the Apoſtle compares them to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> As for example, the Altar of the Iewes with the Table of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and the Table of Chriſtians, with the Table or Altar of Pagans. Iſrael <hi>after the fleſh eates the Sacrifices of fleſh, and are partakers of the Altar</hi> that receives them: ſo are Chriſtians that eate one bread, partakers of that Altar where they receive it: And ſo he expreſſeth it <hi>ver.</hi> 21. <hi>Partakers of the Lords Table:</hi> but you will ſay the phraſes are not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quipollent, becauſe the Apoſtle doth not ſo uſe them. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, they are; for the Table of <hi>Damons,</hi> or dead men is an Altar, as all know, and if I may expound a Pagan Table an Altar, why not a Chriſtian Table an Altar?</p>
                  <p>Will you have it yet more full and plaine? Iewes and Pagans have Tables and Altars, ſo have Chriſtians; they are partakers of their Altars, ſo are Chriſtians; their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation
<pb facs="tcp:21240:9"/>is by eating, ſo is theirs, their eating is Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall or fedorall in the Rites of their Religion, ſo is that of Chriſtians; and in this ſence wee are allowed to make our Covenant. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5. <hi>Call my Saints that have made a Covenant with me by ſacrifices,</hi> which is the fedorall Rite of all Nations; and ſuch is the Sacrament: 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. <hi>The Cup is the New Teſtament in my blood,</hi> that is a fedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Rite of my Covenant with you. Sacrifice or Sacrament, Table or Altar is all one to the Apoſtle, ſo our communion be correſpon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent thereunto.</p>
                  <p>The place to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> is of the ſame ſtampe, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Altar with Altar, and participation with participation: We Chriſtians have an Altar as well as the lewes, wee are partakers of it as well as they, and that by eating which is fedorall and Sacramentall. We deſire not to exclude Chriſt from the Altar, as ſome exclude the Altar from him, more to ſatisfie their owne fancy, than follow the truth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <bibl>Ignat Epiſt. ad Philad.</bibl>
                  </head>
                  <p>His Teſtimony is full in three things: Firſt for the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in plenary words
<note n="a" place="margin">Sacramentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>. Secondly, for the Altar diſtinctly expreſſed
<note n="b" place="margin">Altare. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>. Thirdly, for the Preiſthood fully delivered
<note n="c" place="margin">Sacerdotiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>. To ſay the Altar is Chriſt, is firſt a vaine repetition: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, an impoſſible imagination: for to Chriſt the Altar there needs no Preiſthood, or practice of man, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.2. &amp; 9.11. No humane hands have to doe with this Altar, but the Lord himſelfe; who as he is the Sacrifice and Altar, ſo he is the Preiſt to himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>If any object that one Altar to the whole Church muſt needs be Chriſt, ſeeing in the other ſence wee have many according to the multiude of Churches. I anſwer by the words following, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he underſtands one Biſhop in the place with Presbyters and Deacons, ſo one Church under that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. There is not one univerſall Biſhop to all the world, as Papiſts would have it, and would tryumph in ſuch a teſtimony to advance their Pope. But we underſtand
<pb facs="tcp:21240:10"/>the Father of ſuch a Biſhop, as with Presbyters and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, was appointed to governe the Churches within their owne Iuriſdiction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 4.12, 13. <hi>Philem. ver.</hi> 2. mention <hi>Epaphras Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus</hi> and <hi>Philemon,</hi> for the Church of <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> which had but one Altar or Table for their Communion. The like may be ſaid of <hi>Laodicea</hi> and <hi>Hierapolis,</hi> which ſeeme like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to be under the care of <hi>Epaphras,</hi> and enjoyed but one Table for their Sacrament, as was fit and meet for every congregation. And here we have a double teſtimony of an happy union, ſtrongly confirming the Churches in the ſole interceſſion and mediation of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> For wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe by one Alta, that we have one Mediator; and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of many Altars in one Church dedicated to Saints and Angels, is an argument of Idolatry.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="danger">
               <head>The ſecond danger is the introduction of a Sacrifice, and the deſtruction of a Sacrament.</head>
               <p>To this we ſatisfie in two things: Firſt, every Altar indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth not a ſacrifice, as is plaine; <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 22.23.26. <hi>Wee have not built this Altar to turne from following the Lord, or to offer thereon burnt offerings, or meate offerings, or peace-offerings, or any facrifice, but to be a witneſſe, teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or memoriall, &amp;c.</hi> Origen <hi>in Lev. Hom.</hi> 5. <hi>ſecundum literam non inſtauramus ſacrificia, We according to the letter reſtore no ſacrifice,</hi> but reſt ſatisfied with the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of one ſacrifice once ſacrificed for us. Secondly, every ſacrifice deſtroyes not the Sacrament; and in this I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heare my Ancients ſpeake, than ſpend more words of my owne. <hi>St. Aug. l.</hi> 10. <hi>de Civit. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium quia ſignum veri ſacrifieij. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>ſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt. proſper ſacrificium eſt ſignificante myſterio Epiſt.</hi> 23. <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u Fulgent. lib. ad Petr. Diaconum commemoratio ſacrificij, memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, &amp;c. St. Chryſoſt. in epist. ad Hebr. Hom.</hi> 17. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Aug.
<pb facs="tcp:21240:10"/>Epiſt.</hi> 59. <hi>St. Paul</hi> tells us of the ſacrifice of the Goſpell, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.16. and our Church in the like ſence of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice profeſſed in the Sacrament. <hi>Here we offer and preſent unto thee O Lord, our ſelves, our ſoules, and bodies, to be a reaſonable, holy, and living ſacrifice unto thee.</hi> As in the Goſpell, ſo in the Sacrament of the Goſpell we offer up our ſelves. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Chriſt our Paſſeover is ſlaine for us, therefore let us keepe the Feaſt with ſacrifices of ſincerity and truth:</hi> And becauſe all our actions may be called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thoſe ſacred and Sacramentall Actions of <hi>Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Diſtribution,</hi> and <hi>Participation</hi> at the holy Table may much more be ſo named. The firſt cannot be without prayer, and prayer runnes along with every action: It's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in, and after our receiving, and our booke of common prayers adds further <hi>Our ſacrifice of praiſe and thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving;</hi> and ſo doth <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 50.14. To all which if we adde <hi>Davids</hi> other ſacrifice, we have all ſacrifices <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. that may be required.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="danger">
               <head>The third danger of Tranſubſtantiation and Adoration.</head>
               <p>It were to be wondred if the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould article againſt it ſelfe, and teach us that which it ſo plainely condemneth; read but the Articles of our Church, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, we muſt renounce them before we can beleeve Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, or admit adoration of the Hoſt. <hi>Cornelius de lapide</hi> hath a ſtrange ſaying, and I thinke him more ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid than a ſtone that will beleeve it. In <hi>Iſai. c.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Per verba conſecrationis verè &amp; realiter uti tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur panis, ita producitur, &amp; quaſi generatur in altari a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo potenter &amp; efficaciter, ut ſi Chriſtus necdum eſſet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnatus, per haec verba, Hoc eſt corpus meum, incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur corpuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> humanum aſſumeret, uti graves Theologi d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cent, Sacerd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s eſt quaſi virgo Deipera.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:21240:11"/>
               <head>The dignity of Gods houſe.</head>
               <p>HAving freed you from the danger, let me now deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unto you the dignity of Gods houſe, for majeſty, for mercy, forbeauty, for delight, for order, and happy unity. The firſt place that ever God called his people unto was Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> called his Sanctuary, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.17. a place of majeſty and terrour. In the Tabernacle more mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercy was ſhewed: God deſcending comes downe to them (as it were) in an ambulatory Sanctuary, and walkes as a friend in the midſt of them. From a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle he brings them to a ſtately Temple, and requires to be ſerved in it in the beauty of holineſſe.</p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <lg>
                     <head>It's the very Garden of pleaſure and plenty. <bibl>
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.2.</bibl>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hinc frutices ſurgunt, nitidè &amp; cum floribus herbae,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Balſama cum Caſia, Thus, Myrrha<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Nardus, Amomum,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Narciſſus, Viola, &amp; nimium Roſa plena pudoris:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Acorus, Hyſſopuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, Althaea lavandula, Caltha,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et cum Lactucis, Cariophila Zinziber, illine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ambroſia, &amp; Bacca ſemper frondentis Acanthi;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rutha<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Serpillum<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, &amp; ſuave rubens Hyacinthus, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <lg>
                     <head>A very Heaven upon earth, <bibl>
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1.</bibl>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hinc nitet Arctophilax, oſtentans fulgidus urſas</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Praeluſtres, fulgent hic lactea ſidera Cigni,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pegaſus, Andromede, Cepheuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, &amp; Caſſiopaa,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Orion<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ingens toto reſplendet Olympo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Indo Cants rutilans, ſtellata<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> cernitur Argo;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aſt Argo in ſummâ mieat inclyta ſtella Canopi;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Syrius at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ardens, ſic lucida ſtella Leonis;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hic nelcat alma Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Heſperas, Hermes, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <floatingText type="proof_text">
                  <body>
                     <pb facs="tcp:21240:11"/>
                     <head>A City compact together. <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.3.</bibl>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>In vestra urbe habitat</hi> Eunomia, <hi>pulchra legum modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, ejuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſorores Justitia inviolabilis, fundamentum ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatum, &amp; pax concors conſervatrices opum, auriae filiae Themidis conſili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> valentis, ſtudentes arcere omnem petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantiam, quae faſtus temeraria mater eſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="rule">
               <head>The firſt rule or direction from <hi>St. Paul,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Acts <hi>17.23.</hi>
                  </bibl> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Altars and Images.</head>
               <p>It is cleare by <hi>Celſus,</hi> that Images were made as monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the dead: No man, (ſaith <hi>Celſus) except he bee a very childe, does thinke Images to be Gods, but their ſignes, ſymbols, and monuments;</hi> and being preſſed with the authority of <hi>Heraclitus, the Epheſian Philoſopher, that men did conferre with Images, as if they did talke with their houſes.</hi> To this he thinks his anſwer is ſufficient: yet <hi>Clem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus</hi> the maſter, and <hi>Origen</hi> the ſcholler, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed as unſatisfied, <hi>Protrept. ad Gent. page</hi> 25. <hi>Graecolat. contr. Colſ. l.</hi> 7, <hi>p.</hi> 373, 384. <hi>prodigioſi ſunt qui lapides ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> they are Monſters which make Philoſophicall diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of a true God, and yet worſhip ſtocks and ſtones; how wiſe ſo e're they ſeeme to bee in their owne way, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.22. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they became ſtarke mad. It is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, ſaies <hi>Origen, that one ſhould know God and pray to Images. Iohn.</hi> 4.22. <hi>Yee worſhip yee know not what:</hi> that is, not God as a Spirit, which is the truth; but God as a body, which is a lye. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.18, 19, 20. they muſt needes teach men lies of God; and therefore hee does not onely forbid them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4. but ſhewes by his example, that hee that
<pb facs="tcp:21240:12"/>beſt knew himſelfe, never taught his people by pictures to conceive him <hi>Deut.</hi> 4 12.15. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> laies open all the Pagan myſtery thus: Firſt an Altar, and that ſtood before an Image: the Image was dedicated to a dead man, and the dead man was a mediator to the never dying Diety, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. It is certaine by <hi>Celſus,</hi> that <hi>Pagans</hi> held dead men for inferior Gods, and that they were to the moſt ſupreame God, as <hi>Satrapae &amp; magnates Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum,</hi> as the Peeres and nobles of Princes. St. <hi>Paul</hi> cuts off all this in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>That unknowne God which you ignorantly worſhip in Temples, Altars, Images, and the Dead, him I ſhew unto you.</hi> It is your ignorance to conceive it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for God to have ſuch a habitation, and adoration as you imagine for him, by ſacring of Temples, Altars, and I ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; you ſuppoſe to catch dead mens ſoules, and tye them to your Temples, and having made bodies for thoſe ſoules, you doubt not to call ſuch Images, <hi>ſancta animalia,</hi> holy living things inſpired to doe you good. Upon this ground <hi>Origen, Minutius-Felix, Arnobius,</hi> and <hi>Lactantius,</hi> ſaid, that Chriſtians neither had, nor ought to have <hi>Temples, Altars, Images,</hi> or <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> as if God could not be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped without them, neither was their religion inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and inexplicable, becauſe they wanted ſuch meanes, <hi>non occultamus quod colimus,</hi> wee hide not what we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or have an inviſible faith, or communion within our ſelves; for we profeſſe openly, both what we worſhip, and how we ought to worſhip him, though it be not in your way, which were wickedneſſe and impiety to Ieſus Chriſt; yet had they Temples and Altars for their Saviour, and St. <hi>Iohn</hi> uſeth both words, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1. and 14.17.18. and 16.7. in which both Angels and men doe him ſervice; for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Angels are ſaid to come out of his Temple and Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, where his people worſhip him: and as of old the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle and Temple were called his pallace and throne, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:21240:12"/>where the Arke ſtood; ſo now in the New Teſtament his Temple is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Gods <hi>Baſilica,</hi> eſpecially the place where the Altar ſtands. St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> uſeth both words, and tells us, how the people did συντρέχειν flocke to the Temple and Altar of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Me thinks we ſhould take from him good direction to ſee manifeſt difference betweene Chriſtianity and Pagan Idolatry. We come to our Temples, not as impious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans to tye God to them, we have no βωμὸς before an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, but a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Altar, rightly named before Chriſt Ieſus. This is all we profeſſe, and ſay with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.35. <hi>Iehovah Shamma,</hi> the Lord is <hi>there,</hi> &amp; not the Lord is <hi>this,</hi> and upon his Altar and Temple, wee write as in <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.20, 21. <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord.</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have their Armes and Inſcriptions upon their Chariots, which are not Images of their perſons, but enſignes of their honour God keepe from us σεβάσματα and δαιμόνια, Dead men and their pictures to be worſhipped: and bleſſed be God we have publicke teſtimony by burning their books that maintaine ſuch evills: that wee deteſt their doctrine and practice in this kinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="rule">
               <head>The ſecond rule of St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113</bibl>, Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Images and inſtruments in Gods Worſhip.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Gentiles worſhip that, which they themſelves have made of gold and ſilver. But we alſo have divers inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made of the ſame matter and mettall: For the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Sacraments, which being conſecrated by this very Miniſtry, are called holy, in honour of him, who for our ſalvation is honoured thereby. And theſe Inſtruments and Veſſels, what are they elſe but the worke of mens hands? Yet have they any mouth, and will not ſpeake? have they eyes, and will not ſee? do we ſupplicate to theſe,
<pb facs="tcp:21240:13"/>becauſe by theſe we ſupplicate to God? that is the greateſt cauſe of this mad impiety, that the forme, like unto one li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, which maketh it to be ſupplicated unto, doth more prevaile in the affections of miſerable men, than that it is manifeſt it doth not live at all, that it ought to bee contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by him who is indeed living; for Images prevaile more to bow downe the unhappy ſoule, in that they have a mouth, they have eyes, they have eares, they have noſtrills, they have hands, they have feet: then correct it, that they wil not ſpeake, they will not ſee, they will not heare, they will not ſmell, they will not handle, they will not walke.</hi> Images what they ſeeme to bee, that they are not, and what they are indeede, that they ſeeme not to bee, and ſo bring the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into a double deceite; but inſtruments ſerve truely to the purpoſes, the Church hath appoynted them, and for the ends, the holy Scripture alloweth, in order, decency, and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="rule">
               <head>The third rule is from <hi>St. Iohn</hi> in a neceſſary duty, and decent Ceremony.</head>
               <p>To worſhip the Lambe is without diſpenſation, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration before him admits no prohibition; we periſh if we doe it not. <hi>Pſal</hi> 2.12. But the Ceremony before the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.10. and 7.11. is left us by the example of Elders and Angels: the manner whereof wee know not exactly, and therefore it is wholly left to the Church to preſcribe the forme. St. <hi>Gregor.</hi> ſayes, <hi>in unitate fidei di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa eſt conſuetude,</hi> and St. <hi>Aug.</hi> more fully <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118. <hi>ad Januar. cap.</hi> 22. <hi>in his nulla melior diſciplina prudenti Chriſtiane quam ut eo modo agat, quo agit Eccleſia ad quamcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> devenerit: quod enim nec contra fidom, nec con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra bonos mores iniungitur, indifferenter eſt habendum.</hi> Churches cuſtomes ſhall command me where I ſee they corrupt neither a true faith, nor my duty to God.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21240:13"/>
               <p>I ſhall alwayes wiſh with St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that Churches Ceremonies may have theſe conditions: Firſt, that they be <hi>Numere pauciſſimae.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Obſervatione facillimae.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Significatione utiliſſimae.</hi> I confeſſe, they that can beare none, complaine of all Ceremonies as too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Our wiſdome muſt be, to let them judge, that know better what is good for us than we our ſelves. Study to be as pure as you pleaſe, ſo you be peaceable; and let that property, <hi>Iames</hi> 3.17. take ſpeciall place in you, ἐυπειθ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ς, eaſie to be counſelled, when you cannot counſell your ſelves; and rather yeeld to the Church, than theſe heates of humours, that like an aguiſh diſtemper, will ſuffer you to reliſh nothing. I am reſolved the Scripture will lead no man into an errour, though it may ſeeme to follow it by force: finde but the opinion, and the ſame fancy that found it, hath Scripture to confirme it. Every man ſeekes to eſtabliſh <hi>Non quae vera, ſed quae ſuae eſt opinio;</hi> and wee ſtand in the Church like <hi>Cato</hi> and <hi>Scipio</hi> in the Senate, with <hi>mihi videtur, &amp; mihi non videtur;</hi> and all comes to that end, as a Father complaines, <hi>Inter licet noſtrum, &amp; non li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet veſtrum nutant &amp; remigant animae Chriſtianorum.</hi> God ſtay theſe ſtaggers: It's pitty we ſhould ſtumble upon an Altar, and raiſe an altercation about that, which ſhould be the onely argument of our reconciliation.</p>
               <p>Our Ancients in imitation of our bleſſed Saviour, and his Evangelicall counſell, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.23, 24. proclaimed by the Church-deacons, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Let no man have ought againſt another, but be reconciled, and at peace, before he preſume to come to Gods Altar. It cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cuſtome or Law amongſt the Iewes, ſeeing <hi>Ezech.</hi> 46.10. the very Prince is commanded to come and goe with the people. And <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, the people waited for the Prieſts diſmiſſion. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.21. And we find no tradition of the Elders to urge ſuch a Law as our Saviour inforceth to be followed by his Diſciples. It is moſt Evangelicall, and
<pb facs="tcp:21240:14"/>a degree above Phariſaicall righteouſneſſe, to ſeeke ſuch peace as he preached in the Mountaine, and ſurely not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an eye to our Chriſtian Altar, though it may ſeeme ſomewhat to anticipate the inſtitution of his heavenly Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Would God our comming to one Table, or Altar, might end our ſtrife, and lay aſide a verball contention, to make us reall in that which is materiall, and it ſhall be all our deſire yet further to diſcover the ſame unto you. It is not to be wondred at, that wee read ſo often in Authours ſtraines to our owne ſenſes, and every man is willing to force a Teſtimony to his owne minde. I ſhall wiſh no more than to take my Authour in his owne words, and never uſe corrections that may prove corruptions,
<note place="margin">His cenſure of <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Vedelius</hi> in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, reads <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Senate of ſacrifices, the Senate of Saints,</hi> as more willing to advance the congregation, than the Prieſthood. I hope to bring no Author to my ſelfe, but my ſelfe to them, and leave the evidence to the judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21240:14"/>
            <head>GODS HOVSE AND GODS HONOVR.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 28.17.</hi>
                  </bibl> How dreadfull is this place, this is no other but the Houſe of God, and this is the gate of Heaven.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 35.7.</hi>
                  </bibl> And he built there an Altar and called the place <hi>El-Beth-El:</hi> nothing but Majeſtie inhabits Gods Houſe, and teacheth us to give him honour in it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head type="sub">Deus-Domus-Deus.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Concerning an Inſinuation of the honour due to Gods Houſe, with the heads of the enſuing Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very houſe is knowne beſt by its owner, and it beares his name, great men diſplay their Armes where they are diſpoſed themſelves to live, and their very Chariots have the inſcriptions of their Honour. The Cherubins are called the glory of God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.20. and every place where he appeares takes denomination from him: <hi>Iacob</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21240:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>calls the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place of Gods appearance unto him twiſe by the Name of God, and it teacheth us, what it is that makes a place holy and honourable, even the Name of God, and this remaines at this day in our Temples as a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Gods holineſſe in his Houſe; we neede not aske the queſtion why Gods Houſe is more holy than an other place? or reſolve it as ſome doe upon falſe grounds, of preſence and vertue, either in the people or place it ſelfe: It is not holy becauſe an holy people meete there, or for popular preſence, which is more likely to pollute than ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeto any holineſſe, or for any qualities in it to make them more holy, but becauſe of God whoſe name it beares, and whoſe preſence fills it with the ſignes of his glory; and who there eſpecially ſanctifies and accepts holy ſervice; a Relative, no inherent holineſſe, a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive it is to God and not to men, his houſe it is, not theirs, whereſoever God men and Angells meete, and are made knowne one to another by voyce and viſion, there is Gods Houſe and holineſſe; when God appeared to <hi>Iacob</hi> and ſpake unto him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. the bleſſed Angells accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied him, and waited upon him in the Ladder of his Providence, and aſſured <hi>Iacob</hi> that they would goe with him in every ſteppe of his journey, both forward and backward: Nay, <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaw in his journey the very ladder of heaven, and his way to eternall happineſſe, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 1.51. and 8.56. It would be obſerved what made the place dreadfull, and yet a gate of heaven, <hi>Surely the Lord is in this place and I knew it not.</hi> Ignorance of an inviſible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence deprives us of our comfort therein, and therefore God by viſion and voyce ſo workes upon our eyes and eares, that they may let in Majeſtie and mercie together, Power and Compaſſion, Grace and Glory, &amp;c. Theſe ſignes want not their uſe in our dayes, and deliver us our duties in the like expreſſions of Majeſtie to us: Our ſignes are milder, yet not leſſe Majeſticall than of old, now wee are all ſo for voyces, that we in a manner contemne all Viſions, and our eares are ſo open to hearing, that we heed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21240:15"/>not what our eyes ſhould turne us unto. When God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Moſes Exod</hi> 3. hee had a Viſion and a Voyce; when he appeared to <hi>Ezekiel, Ezek.</hi> 1.28. he had the like; <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> had both of them Viſions and Voyces to direct them, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. And as in the extraordinary, God takes this way upon him, ſo in the ordinary courſe he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the ſame, and ſets before us, as well ſignes of his Preſence, as Voyces to informe us; Maſſe is made a matter of juſt reproach to them that take away the teaching and intelligible voice to turne it into the pleaſure of the eyes? yet there be of itching eares too, that ſteppe over duties and looke not to their feete, when they enter conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted places to give God any honour at his memoriall in his Houſe, and ſight of any ſigne of his preſence: They ſay they are ready to heare a good dutie, but that is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, if they conſider not the preſence of God &amp; Angels in the place, and give not ſome teſtimony more than the eare, that they come to obey; Remember the houſe and the honour that I ſhall in this Diſcourſe ſet before thee, and eſteeme better of the place for his ſake that ownes it, and to whom thou oweſt humble ſervice, I meane to ſpeake of Gods Houſe in all the partitions of it, and to vindicate to my power all his honour in making him the onely object of divine worſhip in it, my indeavour ſhall be to uſe Gods Word and Church cuſtomes as candles to light us, and not as clouds to hinder our ſight. The <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> by beholding the Sunne and Moone become Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in odoring of them, but <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 8.3. makes a better uſe to ſee in them a finger of the divine power, and ſo conſidered as the ſtarre led to Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2. they ſerve to lead the quicke to the living God, &amp; not to dead Idolls. The over ſuſpitions of ſuperſtition, become moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperſtitious to avoid it, and who can hinder the forge of a ſeduced heart to forme what fancie it luſteth, waves beating againſt a rocke are diſſolved into froth, and every imagination againſt the truth is as an haſtie purſuit run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21240:16"/>out of the way, and like hounds that are ſwift of foote but not exquiſite in ſent, which ſpend their mouthes and courſes in vaine [Our inſolent Separatiſts having hiſſed a while like Snakes, turne themſelves into fiery Dragons, and ſpit out all the poyſon they can againſt us. Other adverſaries wee have that like the <hi>Panther</hi> into which the Dragon creepes in the <hi>Revelation</hi>] ſeeke to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us by ſubtiltie,
<note place="margin">Rev. 13.2.</note> in whoſe wiles many are caught before they be aware, and before they attend to keepe him at a diſtance. It is not without cauſe that the Dragon is ſaid to have the <hi>Panther</hi> for his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, for Satan is ſubtill to change his skinne, and doe the ſame miſchiefe in a more ſecret, as in an open evill way. <hi>Pagan</hi> Idolatry is odious to all Chriſtians, and the ſhew of the Dragon is enough to make them flie him:
<note place="margin">Rev. 13.1.</note> but ſee, when God brings him to his ſtand, and drives him to vaniſh where hee had his firſt originall, yet the Text ſayes <hi>he ſtood upon the ſand of the ſea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 7.3.</note> and gave way to the <hi>Panther</hi> to riſe out of it and ſucceede him, πάνθηρ <hi>dictus quod omnium animalium amicus ſit excepto dracone.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſidor. c.</hi> 12.2.</note> The <hi>Panther</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi> are the greateſt oppoſites, and ſo is Pagan and Chriſtian Religion, but the devill will deviſe their reconciliation, and make friends of the greateſt foes: The <hi>Panther</hi> is ſo called becauſe he is a friend of all Bruits, except the Dragon [The Cannon doth not ſo much hurt againſt a wall, as a myne under it, nor a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand enemies that threaten, ſo much as a few that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire and take an oath to ſay nothing. Gods Houſe and Honor are much ſuſpected, and many accuſed and libelled againſt, as if they were the <hi>Panthers</hi> of our time: ſo that now we ſuſpect all; but certainely we muſt either bluſh for ſhame, or grow pale for feare, our accuſations may ſhame us if we cannot prove them, and our puniſhments apale us that wee caſt our ſelves into priſon and perills, becauſe we are peeviſh interpreters of the minds of our Superiours. My labour at this time ſhall be to ſelect ſome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21240:16"/>one ſentence that may ſet us on worke, to ſee and ſearch if there be as great cauſe as we complaine there is of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of our preſent times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 7.11. <hi>And all the Angells ſtood round about the Throne, and about the Elders, and the foure beaſts, and fell before the Throne on their face, and worſhipped God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gods Houſe or honourable Pallace hath the partition according to the perſons, firſt in reſpect of God,
<note place="margin">The ſeates of the Elders. The foure Beaſts.</note> here is a <hi>Throne,</hi> ſecondly in reſpect of his Miniſters, there be <hi>ſedes ſeniorum, Rev.</hi> 4.4. thirdly, in reſpect of the people; there be foure <hi>Animalia,</hi> or as <hi>David</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.10. and the <hi>Septuagint</hi> tranſlates it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and S.
<note place="margin">The people ordered in their ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards dwelt in it.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> reades it <hi>Animalia tua habitaverunt in ea,</hi> that is (the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ordered in their ſtandards dwelt in it;) fourthly, in reſpect of the Angells, there is their round and guard ſet in the Houſe of God, they are the cheefe attendants upon the Majeſtie of God, and where he places his Court or Sanctuary, there doe they give their attendance, and therefore in Gods Houſe wee are bidden looke to our words, becauſe we are before <hi>Gods Angells,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eecle. 5.6. 1 Cor. 11.10.</note> and women are bidden to weare a veile, which as their haire is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally given them for a covering, may be a ſigne of their modeſtie, and being under covert and ſubjection, <hi>Becauſe of the Angells.</hi> This made <hi>Jacob</hi> in his journey count the place dreadfull, where God and his Angells appeared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: In the words of the text without ſtraining them, Gods Houſe upon earth, in all the parts of it: There is the place of Majeſtie, called <hi>the throne of the Lambe,</hi> ſecondly, the place of the Miniſtry called <hi>the ſeates of the Elders;</hi> thirdly the place of Auditory, called the <hi>foure beaſts,</hi> or ſtandards of the people; fourthly, the place of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly gard, called <hi>the round of the Angells.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The honor is anſwerable to the houſe, and it may be for our better method divided into foure parts, 1. the object which is no (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or σέβασμα) Altar or Idoll,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.23.</note> but God alone: They worſhipped not the Throne when they fell
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21240:17"/>downe before it but God, and therefore the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſhamefull of many in our Kingdome, that they worſhip the Altar when they bow downe before it; I might as well accuſe the holy Angells to worſhip the throne, becauſe they fell downe before it, as many blame thoſe for worſhipping the Altar who bow towards the holy Table or Altar, ſuch fault finders will not diſcerne that the bowing is before the Altar the adoration to God —and a like howſoever the holy Table be ſited. But ſome will be wiſe to make others wicked, and holy to make others thought horrible Idolaters worſe than any; for I never yet read of any that worſhipped Altars, Idolls by ſome, and Images by others, upon or above Altars, I know have beene and are ſtill worſhipped, and therein the <hi>Panther</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi> are reconciled; <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts leaped upon their Altar, and it may be upon their God too, to awaken him and ſhed their bloud in ſacrifice upon him, but I doe not heare they adored their Altar, or called upon it, but <hi>heare us O Baall;</hi> ſecondly, as God is the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of divine honour, ſo the kinde of honour that is due to God, and him alone is worſhip and adoration. <hi>Arrius</hi> was not onely an hereticke in denying the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, but an Idolater in worſhipping the bare Manhood, we may honour Angells and Saints, but wee may not worſhip them; every one that worſhippeth honoureth, but not on the contrary, every one that honoreth adoreth, Its Gods prerogative Royall, and ſo incommunicable that none may partake with God in this honour: thirdly, wee have the moſt humble geſture expreſſed in this honour, and that is <hi>prostration.</hi> The very Angells of God may teach us reverend geſtures in the Houſe of God; fourthly, here is the directing of the geſture, and thats <hi>towards the Throne:</hi> Gods people in captivity were to looke towards <hi>Iudea,</hi> in <hi>Iudea</hi> towards <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> towards the <hi>Temple,</hi> in the <hi>Temple</hi> towards the <hi>Mercie ſeate;</hi> when we pray in Gods Houſe, we muſt turne our face towards
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21240:17"/>the Throne of Majeſtie, and ſo doe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Elders, as well as the Angells, <hi>Revel.</hi> 4.10. the text ſingled out will talke with our times, God inable me to give the right ſenſe, for I will ſeeke to ſtraine nothing, but as cloſely as I can cleare every paſſage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the place of Majestie in the Church, that is, the holy Table or Altar, and the incloſure thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the place of Majeſtie in the Houſe of God, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> hath given it the name, either in the Altar, or place of it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.18. and 16.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The Angells that are Gods attendants in Gods Houſe goe out and in as he commands them: They doe not goe into the Altar and out of it, and therefore <hi>Beza</hi> boldly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates the one place <hi>ab Altari,</hi> from the Altar, and the other <hi>E Sanctuario,</hi> out of the Sanctuary, neither is he ſenſeleſſe therein, for <hi>ab Altari</hi> ſhewes the terme from which the motion begins, and <hi>E Sanctuario,</hi> the place out of which they move; and the bleſſed Angells wait both upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar and ſtand in the Sanctuary to do ſervice as the are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. It was a fearefull voyce in the Sanctuary (<hi>Teſt. Joſeph. de Bello Iudaico, l.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.) which often in the night was heard, ſounding theſe words, <hi>Let us goe hence,</hi> undoubtedly it was the voyce of thoſe bleſſed Spirits for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the Temple, and leaving it to the rage of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes:</hi> In the captivitie, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 10.4. the glory of the Lord departed from the place of Majeſtie, firſt to the threſhold, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.3. ſecondly above it, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 10.4. Theſe were the firſt warnings in open view, thirdly, the glory returnes to call out the Cherubins themſelves, and they preſent themſelves at the Eaſt gate with their wings and wheeles, and the glory of God over them, as ready all at once to be gone, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 10.18.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21240:18"/>fourthly, from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gate of the Temple, and the midſt of the city the glory of the Lord departeth and ſtands upon the mountaine, which is on the Eaſt ſide of the citty, <hi>Eze.</hi> 11.23. The captivitie of the Temple comes a pace when the glory of God is gone from it, I ſay thats the place of Majeſtie where God ſheweth the ſignes of his preſence, aad ſends his Angells to give their attendance.</p>
               <p>In the new Teſtament, the Sanctuary or chiefe place of Majeſtie, is where the Altar ſtands, for the word ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſignifies an Altar or the place where it ſtands. It was not ſo in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for all their Altars were placed out of the holy of holies, God did ſhut up himſelfe in the place of Majeſtie, and gave no admittance but to the high Prieſt once a yeare to enter that ſacred place, but now it is more common and of daily uſe for Gods people, yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction, as we ſee it is conſtantly obſerved by Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Booke of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> for theſe foure parts are never confounded, but alwayes recited with their due diſtinctions and diſtances: In Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and it is concluded of the whole Church of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> as a conſtant and common cuſtome of ſpeech to call the place of Majeſtie <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and I know no reaſon of the appellation but from the Altar, which the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther calls by the name of the holy table, but not ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely as ſome call it now, and count Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to be of their minds, who ſo calls it every where as they ſay, and no where an Altar, which if it were granted, could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude nothing for them, that therefore of purpoſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from the name of an Altar any more than Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> Neither is it to be ſhunned either in reſpect of <hi>Iewes</hi> or <hi>Pagans,</hi> for the <hi>Pagans</hi> never uſed the word for an altar, but βωμὸς, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth <hi>Act.</hi> 17.23. and I beleeve upon curious ſearch the word will be found meerely Eccleſiaſticall, and uſed onely by Churchmen, and therefore we neede not to avoid it as a <hi>Pagan</hi> word, as they have avoided βωμὸς, which I never read was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21240:18"/>given to Gods Altar, neither is it to be avoided in reſpect of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> for Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> uſeth it often in application to Chriſtians and the ſervice of Chriſt, S. <hi>Paul</hi> avoides it not in the meaning, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Flee from Idolatrie,</hi> his arguments are two, one from the <hi>Iewes, verſ.</hi> 18. another from the <hi>Pagans, verſ.</hi> 20. partakers of the legall ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are partakers of the legall Altars, and ſuch is our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, as our ſervice of him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10. <hi>We have an Altar whereof they have no right to eate, which ſerve the Tabernacle.</hi> They that ſticke to <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt Chriſt cannot be partakers of Chriſt, Chriſts Altar and a Iewiſh Altar cannot ſtand together, <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the fleſh eates the ſacrifices of fleſh, and partakes with an altar of fleſh, and therefore cannot partake with Chriſt. The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is undeniable, that the Communion is according to the ſervice, and therefore to eate with Idolaters, in Idolatrous Temples, at Idolatrous Tables is Idolatrie, and we are to flee the Communion if we will avoide the corruption; I ſay the holy Apoſtle aymes not in a Table to avoid the name of an Altar or of a ſacrifice, but of the Communion. The Table in the Temple of Idolaters is an Altar, their meate and drinke offerings ſacrifices. They both eate and offer: but firſt offer and then eate; for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon things cannot be ſacred to God, till wee both ſet them apart, and ſanctifie them for the uſe of his ſervice, for nothing is <hi>Deo ſacrum,</hi> which is not <hi>Deo oblatum,</hi> The very ſeparation is to God, that he might ſanctifie unto us what we firſt offer unto him; S. <hi>Paul</hi> makes communion oblation, participation, &amp;c. to ſound all to one ſenſe, we other the with to God that it may be bleſſed, he gives the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p to us with the bloud of his Sonne, the Cup is the Communion of bloud; call a Table an Altar, and an Altar a Table for me without offence, ſo I am ſure <hi>Ezekiel</hi> does, <hi>Chap.</hi> 41.32. and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſeconds him, <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> for ought I know might have called the Table of the Lord an Altar, as well as hee calls the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21240:19"/>Altar of devills a Table. But we are intended in our dayes to wrangle and wreſt all truths to oppoſe adverſaries, more than confirme them by faire and faſt binding our ſelves to give them intertainement in their beſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations.</p>
               <p>It pleaſeth the Holy Ghoſt as farre as I can apprehend it, to call the place of Majeſtie the Sanctuary in Gods Houſe, or the place where Gods Table or Altar ſtandeth; for this purpoſe, I have produced both <hi>Beza</hi> a moderne Divine, and Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> a more antient Writer, and will now proceede to ſay more from <hi>Theodoret, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>lib.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Zorrat, Hiſt. lib. cap.</hi> 25. <hi>Zozom. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 28. from <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his Panegyrick Oration at the dedication of the Temple of <hi>Tyre,</hi> from the Council of <hi>Laeodicia, Can.</hi> 44. ſixt Councill in <hi>Trullo Can.</hi> 69. <hi>Concil. Arcl. Can.</hi> 15. <hi>Concil. Conſtant.</hi> 5. and 6. <hi>Can.</hi> 69 Saint <hi>Cypr. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 9. and from Saint <hi>Ignatius,</hi> I ſhall leave my Reader to enlarge himſelfe, and onely ſet before his eyes what I have ſearched for my owne ſatisfaction. I will beginne with <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour, and Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, the Emperour enters the Church at <hi>Millaine</hi> to act his ſolemne reverence, and his firſt reverence is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his whole body, uſing the words of the <hi>Pſalme</hi> 119.25. <hi>adheſit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> men, &amp;c.</hi> my foule e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to the pavement, in humility of ſoule and body hee kiſſeth the very duſt and ſtones wherewith the Church was paved, and powred forth his teares abundantly: and preparing himſelfe to receive the Sacrament; (which is enough to ſtricke dead the point in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with equall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he went up the ſteppings of the Altar, I may have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> amiſſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>palatium in gonere,</hi> Gods houſe <hi>in ſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> called <hi>Baſilica,</hi> but thats not enough here, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the plurall number ſignifies the degrees or ſteppings to the Altar, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 5. when he came to the Royall ſtay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> be <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> againe as abundantly as when he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21240:19"/>firſt entred the Church. Then according to his cuſtome at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> he went within the raile, but S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> by a Deacon <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hee taught him that places were to be diſtinguiſhed in the Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that it was for Prieſts and not for Princes to come within the rayle, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, come forth and communicate with thine owne ranke, and remember in Gods Houſe to hold the perfect paterne of the difference and diſtinction,
<note place="margin">Purple makes Kings not Prieſts.</note> of a Prince and a Prieſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Princes robes and Prieſts ornaments are not alike, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are their places. At the Councill in <hi>Trullo Can.</hi> 69. <hi>Non licet ulli corum omnium qui in laicorum numero ſunt, ingredi intra ſanctu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Altare nequaquam tamen ab eo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibita poteſtate &amp; authoritate imperiali, quandocunque vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>catori dona offerre ex antiquiſſima traditione;</hi> It is not lawfull for any that be in the number of Laicks to enter within the raile of the holy Altar; yet the Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie and Authoritie is not thereby prohibited ingreſſe when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he hath a will to offer any gifts to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour by a moſt antient tradition, for the moſt antient uſe of the Church was, that lay Chriſtians might have acceſſe to the Altar to preſent there their eſpeciall devotions, or receive Prieſtly abſolution, &amp;c. otherwiſe they were not to enter, but receive the bleſſed Euchariſt, and place themſelves without the raile, as the Councill of <hi>Laodicia</hi> is expreſſe for women. Saint <hi>Ignatius</hi> who lived in the Apoſtles dayes, <hi>Epiſt. ad Trallens, Qui extra Altare est, eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> qui five Epiſcop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; presbite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is &amp; Dioconis ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Qui eſt extra Altare, ille pollutu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; eſt in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idels deterior,</hi> He which is without the Altar is hee who does ought without the Biſhop, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Deacon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and againe, hee who is without the Altar he is polluted in conſcience, and worſe than an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>, where he is ſaid to be without the Altar, not who may not come within the raile, but who may not partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21240:20"/>of the holy Table, for ſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church Canons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him: and in ſuch caſe are all our Conventicle kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that both without and againſt lawfull Biſhops and Prieſts walke their owne bywayes. As Chriſt was knowne to his two diſciples in breaking of bread; ſo were the Primitive Prieſts knowne to their people by breaking the Sacramentall bread, and it was held the ſymbole of Chriſtian Communion to be partakers of the Altar, and to receive from it the holy Sacraments, <hi>Ignat. ad Tralleuſſ. qui intra Altare eſt, purus eſt, igitur &amp; obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Epiſcop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Presbyteris,</hi> he who is within the Altar is pure, therefore alſo he obeyeth the Biſhop and Prieſts. He is within the Altar that may receive the Sacrament, and he onely may receive the Sacrament that is in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or due order, ſubject to the Biſhop and Prieſts: <hi>Sine his Eccleſia electa non eſt, non caetus ſanctorum, non congregati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſanctorum,</hi> without theſe there is no elect Church, no obſervation of holy things, no congregation of Saints, <hi>ad Epheſ. Epiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> he that is not within the Altar is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the Bread of God, that is, he that hath no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with his Paſtor at the Altar, is to be denied the Sacrament, ſtill the Altar hangs upon the <hi>Prieſt;</hi> and fellowſhip with him proves fellowſhip with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Apoſtles Doctrine, fellowſhip, prayers, and breaking of bread are all cloſely compriſed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by this Father, <hi>Epiſt. ad Magn.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in faith and concord, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>praeſidente Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dei lot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the Biſhop being preſident over them in the place of God; the Biſhop ſucceede the Apoſtles in plenarie power; the Presbitere the ſeventie whom our Saviour adjoyned to his Apoſtles. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that ſuch a Senate might meete to conſider of matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of peace and truth. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that all might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in one place to pray, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21240:20"/>runne to the Temple of God, as to one place of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, or one Altar, and one Ieſus Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are as one, for the whole Church is Gods Palace, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the place of his Altar where the people are made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Chiſt himſelfe, Temple muſt be taken away ſayes <hi>Vedelius,</hi> as a corruption contrary to thoſe times that profeſſed they had no Temples, and ſo muſt Altars too, for they profeſſed againſt them, and then nothing is left but Ieſus Chriſt who muſt be found out of Temples, and Altars too may be in the Deſert and ſecret chambers, where there is neither the Apoſtles Doctrine, fellowſhip, breaking of bread or prayers; but a confuſed rabble with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all order or obſervation of Gods Ordinances, as hee hath appointed them, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by Saint <hi>Iohn Rev.</hi> 14.17, 18. in ſuch a ſenſe as they ought to be, where God, Angells, and men meete, and as the whole place may be called Gods Houſe or Temple, ſo the Sanctuary or Altar is the ſpeciall place of Majeſtie,
<note place="margin">One Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, one Fleſh, one Bloud, one Bread, one Cup, one Altar.</note> 
                  <hi>Epi. ad Philad.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, here I am ſure is the Sacrament with all the ſignes and the things ſignified, and what ſhall the Altar be? Chriſt will ſome ſay is one Altar to all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, for Tables they may have many. Not ſo, but as there is to us one Chriſt, ſo one Altar, and we profeſſe no more to expreſſe the Majeſtie of our God,
<note place="margin">There is one Altar for the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</note> many Altars in one Church were never heard of in the moſt Primitive times, let theſe looke to them that undertake their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, for I ſay with S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The fiſt generall Councell ſpeakes of concourſe to the Altar, that there was running <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> hath <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.4. and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>v.</hi> 6. All I ſeeke for, is ſome ſympathie betwixt the holy Scriptures and Primitive practiſes. A throne of Majeſtie there is in the Houſe of God, or ſome viſible ſigne of Gods inviſible preſence to make the partition as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> hath ſet it downe. At the Dedication of the Temple of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21240:21"/>
                  <hi>Tyre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> I read of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, compaſſed about with neate workes,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he holy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and the reverent placing of <hi>Pauline</hi> the Biſhop with his clergie in <hi>Cathedra,</hi> and <hi>Exedris</hi> about it; I reade of <hi>Alexander</hi> the holy Biſhop of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Arrius</hi> and the deſperate ſtorme threatened againſt him, and the Orthodox faith to have fallen at the foote of the Altar and proſtrate to Almightie God, to have prayed that God would evert that judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from his poore Church, &amp;c. I conceive wee may well conjecture we are not farne from the ſenſe, the ſame ſence may yet further be fetched from three places of Scripture, to which he alludeth in the expreſſion of the Chriſtian Theatre upon which God repreſents his glory in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21240:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Touching the Throne of Majeſtie in</hi> Sinai, <hi>and the Tabernacle, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt he alluds to <hi>Sinai</hi> Gods firſt glorious Sanctuarie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men,
<note place="margin">Rev. 4.5.</note> as may appeare by <hi>Lightnings and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and voyces</hi> which iſſue out of the Throne, as they did upon <hi>Sinai</hi> when God appeared, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. and in theſe declared his Majeſtie, and ſet bounds to all Iſrael to be kept with the greateſt diligence, leaſt danger befall the intruders to their ruine; God made all the Mount the place of his Maieſtie, and he himſelfe ſpake in terrour to his people, ſo that they petitioned there might be a middle betweene them and him, and that <hi>Moſes</hi> and men like themſelves might ſpeak, and that firſt diviſion of Majeſtie and auditory, of God ſpeaking and men bearing being too terrible, might be turred into a more milde and middle way of Miniſterie intervening betweene himſelfe and them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24. The multitude are to keepe the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not to ſtirre at all to draw any nearer to God, <hi>Aaron, Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu with ſeventy Elders</hi> are to goe u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with <hi>Moſes</hi> into the Mount, and there muſt they Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>weene God and the people; whiles God gives the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>fect patterne of all things in the Mount, he makes the Mount the firſt draught, and drawes the forme in the place of their ſtanding, as a throne of Majeſtie, ſeates of Elder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and a boundarie for the people, and the bleſſed Angells to keepe their rounds and gaurds of attendance in all places as God appoints them.
<note place="margin">Exod. 24 10.17.</note> Majeſtie is in the pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and where the feete of the Almightie plant them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, there is as the body of heaven in his cleareneſſe, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Maunt was like devouring fire, and all to ſet forth his glorie that is moſt inviſible: No picture of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21240:22"/>God, but paſſing ſignes of his preſence, and warnings which way they were to worſhip him, and be wrought into an holy feare of ſo dreadfull a God, as hee ſhewed himſelfe to be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſaid expreſſions: God is farre more milde in the Chriſtian Church, and his Sanctuarie is ſet upon Mount Sion which may be approached, and from whence God ſpeaketh more mildly unto us, and in which the innumerable company of Angells keepe their watch. I ſee not out the holy Table may be ſet as a ſigne to diſtinguiſh the place of Majeſtie from all the reſt: Our Antients made that Regall which was in the ſteppings and degrees of the Altar, and therefore the Altar much more may expreſſe Majeſtie. If any aske me why is God in one part of the Church more than an other, and why is one part more holy than another? I anſwer it is not from any inheſſion or incluſion of God and holineſſe in that place, as <hi>Pagans</hi> imagine in their Temples where they include their Gods. Againſt theſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> diſputes at <hi>Athens,</hi> and ſo doe <hi>Origen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Minuti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Felix, Arnob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> and <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tantius,</hi> and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ried downe Temples and Altars: for ſuch Temples, Alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, and Images, as they confute are impious and forbidden to Chriſtians, becauſe the Heathen did <hi>Revoca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mortuorum ad Templa, Altaria, Imagines,</hi> revoke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſoules of the dead to Temples, Altars, Images, and put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n them <hi>Divinas virtut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, &amp;c.</hi> they placed divine vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> in their Temples, Altars, and Images, and ſought for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by their preſence, as being filled with Celeſtiall power to do them good; but we beleeve of our Temples and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> did, that God is in them of grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to his people, and that they are holy in relation to him, as the Houſe is his, the Table his, where he will feede his people, and fill them with his favours. It pleaſeth him to have his Throne, and as ever, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t of Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie which he daily opens to his people, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them to his heavenly Table. His Table is enough to make
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21240:22"/>it holy, and ſeparate from common uſe, and to be the dayly monument of divine benediction where Church Prayers have beene ſaid, nay have the preferment, and be counted the moſt ſacred place in Gods Houſe, in which hee offers himſelfe to his people, and they take him, as truely preſent; for reall preſence is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when tranſubſtantiation is rejected, but Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally preſent i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the holy Sacrament is an object of our faith, not of our ſight or ſeene, as Gods Houſe and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour goe together: ſo the chiefe place invites the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God towards it, according to the decencie of Religion. Secondly, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> alludes to the Tabernacle in the Wilderneſſe, and Temple in <hi>Canaan,</hi> as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the <hi>Lampes of fire and Sea of Glaſſe.</hi> Now that in both theſe were diſtinctions, as the Court of Majeſtie, Court of Miniſtry, and Court of Auditory it needes not inqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing. The Tabernacle in the Wilderneſſe, which in the whole is often called Gods Throne, was pitched about in that goodly order, that the Prieſts and Levites encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped next to the whole Tabernacle, the people at a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſtance, <hi>Num.</hi> 6.2. and as ſome imagine two <hi>Engliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> miles. Their doores were to open upon the Sanctuary, and they were to doe their devotion, both going out and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in: ſo that when the Sanctuary was open for ſervice, there was a threefold diviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, into the couit of the people, court of the Prieſts, and Court of God; when it was ſhut up the diviſion was three fold, the Tabernacle, the Campe of the Prieſts and Levites, and the foure Campes of Iſrael under 4. ſtandats, as we ſhall heare afterwards. The Arke, the Mercy-ſeate are often called Gods Footeſtoole, and his Throne. Laſtly, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſhewing Gods little Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie in the <hi>Babilonian</hi> captivitie and deſtruction of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> Temple teacheth the ſame, where we have foure Beaſts, and over them a <hi>Firmament,</hi> and above that a <hi>Thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, Eze.</hi> 1. The foure Beaſts may well point at the foure Standards of the twelve Tribes. To the <hi>Eaſt</hi> was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21240:23"/>
                  <hi>Judah, Iſachar</hi> and <hi>Zabulon,</hi> with the Enſigne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a <hi>Lyon;</hi> to the <hi>South, Ruben, Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Gad,</hi> under the ſigne of a man in the flagge: To the <hi>Weſt, Ephraim, Manaſſes</hi> and <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> with the banner bearing the ſigne of a <hi>Bullocke.</hi> To the <hi>North, Dan, Aſhur</hi> and <hi>Naphtali</hi> bearing the Enſigne of an <hi>Eagle:</hi> Its probable that <hi>Ezechiel</hi> hath this meaning, if we marke his ſtanding, looking into the North the place of the captivitie of <hi>Iudah, Ezeck.</hi> 1.4. the firſt face that meetes him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. is the face of a <hi>man,</hi> and thats <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens</hi> quarter to lie upon the South, on his right hand is the Eaſt, and on that ſide appeares a Lyon, where <hi>Iudah</hi> quartered, on the left ſide the face of an <hi>Oxe,</hi> and thats the Weſt, where <hi>Ephraim</hi> encamped. The North needes no character, and that is the face of an <hi>Eagle</hi> where <hi>Dan</hi> was appointed to pitch about the Tabernacle, ſo that foure Beaſts are characters of the places of Gods people, when they forme a part of Gods Houſe or Sanctuary. The <hi>Firmament</hi> or <hi>expanſe</hi> is now the voide place where God may be heard and ſeene of his people: The Beaſts let downe their wings and ſtand in ſilence, and from the Firmament above them, a voyce is uttered, &amp;c. This is the middle ſpace betwixt God and his people. Above this appeares the Throne, and one in the appearance of a man ſitting upon it: here is mention of <hi>precious ſtones</hi> as in Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> and of a <hi>Rainebow,</hi> and all together ſhew our diſtinction of the place of Majeſtie, Miniſtery and Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and Angells of God as ſecret ſpirits to keepe their rounds and guards as God himſelfe that guides all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; and that of the Throne of Majeſtie, which God hath alwayes had it in his Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21240:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the ſeates of the Elders, the ſtation of Biſhops and Prieſts that ſerve at the Altar.</hi> Sedes Seniorum.</head>
               <p>HAving done with the Throne of the Lambe, wee ſeeke for the Thrones of his ſervants, or ſeates of ſuch Elders, as he ſelects to fit about him; in heaven all Saints ſit downe with Chriſt in glory, but their ſeverall ſeates are higher one than other according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in grace here, none attaining to the ſeate of Chriſt, which is the Throne of Gods Majeſtie farre above all principalities, &amp;c. In the Church militant on earth, Chriſt chuſes Miniſters to ſit downe in ſeates under him for the government of his Church; but it is wrong to the Lord Ieſus to lift one man out of the ſeates of the Elders into the ſeate of the Lambe, and ſet him above all the reſt in ſuch abſolute and ſoveraigne authoritie as is onely due to Chriſt himſelfe, who is not abſent from his ſeate, but in grace and holy concourſe is with his Miniſters in their ſeates to the end of the world, where two or three of them are gathered together in his name, there is he in the middeſt of them: hee may allu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to the ſetting up ſeates for judgment in Iſrael: The greateſt number we reade of in that Nation was ſeventie or ſeventie one, the leſſer 23. the leaſt three. <hi>Duo qui judicant eorum non eſt judicium,</hi> when two Judge they have no Judgement, becauſe they want a caſting voyce, yet our Saviour ſpeaks of two agreeing, having power to judge, and to whom he gives the Keyes, <hi>Math.</hi> 18.16.17.18, 19, 20. that hee will anſwer to whatſoever they aske and ratifie their ſentences: He makes good the ſeates of his Elders in all places, and gives them authoritie to bind and looſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21240:24"/>and retaine all ſinnes. Wee will inquire further of the number, names, offices, ornaments, order of theſe Elders in Gods Houſe, and before his Throne: the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Seates and Elders conſiſts of 24. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.4.19. The expoſition is eaſie, as Gods Houſe was ordered in the ſervice of it by 24. Orders or courſes of Prieſts, ſo now is it ſerved by the like number of Presbiters, yet their honor is greater, as having ſeates and great authoritie. <hi>Luke</hi> in the <hi>Acts</hi> tells them the Apoſtles fellowſhip: and holy <hi>Ignatius</hi> joyning with the Biſhops the Presbiters, calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Epiſt. ad Magn.</hi> A Synod appointed of God to ſerve at the ſeate of his Majeſtie, for his Throne were emptie without them; for Biſhops with their El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders we have chaires and ſeates warranted both by Gods Word, and the antient practice of the Church, ſee <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> with his Presbiters at the dedication of the Temple of <hi>Tyre,</hi> and you ſhall be taught to learne a good leſſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Papiſts and Schiſmatickes in our dayes, that ding downe with their Axes and Hammers the ſeates and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties of Gods Elders; one Pope muſt Lord it over all, and have a ſeate above all Biſhops. In the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip no ſuch thing is to be found, and when the Fathers alleadge their ſeates againſt Schiſmatickes, they never make one ſeate the rule of all: Our Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes that paſſe from us and reject the ſeates of Biſhops, and ſet up a lay-elderſhip, and put them into chaires to judge, I marvell whence they have it, for all the Presbyters in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>it of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Theologie are Prieſts. A ſtrange ſucceſſion they will make in Gods Houſe, and bring into the Apoſtles fellowſhip, no breakers of bread, but Church Canons, no Prieſts to pray to the people, but to prate againſt them, and to take the higheſt place of a ſeate to judge. Its the Fathers wiſedome againſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them onely by the Word of God; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Schiſmatickes to condemne them wholly by the Chaires of the Church; and ſure I am againſt theſe ſeates
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21240:24"/>they cannot ſtand out, and as in <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 7.64. they that wanted a Regiſter to reckon their Genealogie were put from the Prieſthood as poluted, ſo theſe that contemne the chaires of Biſhops, and care for no Epiſcopall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but will ſucceede where was never ſucceſſion: As to have Miniſters from Magiſtrates, and men never or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by others, is to caſt themſelves from all commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Church, which never held any that was not ſucceſſively from the Apoſtles. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth himſelfe to be an Apoſtle, but neither of man nor by man, neither of man as the author, nor by man as the inſtrument, but immediatly of God and by God, as author and meanes of his vocation. A plaine diſtinction of a threefold calling, whereof two are as the extreames, and the third as a meane betweene both, firſt ſome are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of God and by God immediatly, and this is the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary calling of Prophets and Apoſtles, who are the firſt founders of our Religion, and the chiefe Governors under Ieſus Chriſt, Secondly, ſome are called <hi>of men and by men,</hi> and ſuch are all humane callings in Gods Church; I deny not but many may be appointed to doe ſervice in the Church that have no divine calling, but that which is meerely of men, and ſuch are Church-wardens, Sides<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, yea and higher callings, as Chancellors and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Judges which are lay-men, whoſe authoritie is no more contrarie to Gods Word, than the appointment of ſeven Overſeers for the poore, or Church treaſurie, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.3. <hi>Looke you out ſeven men, &amp;c.</hi> I finde no other election made but this in all the New Teſtament, that in the <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Ordination of Elders by election,</hi> is both a corruption of the text and of the truth, for none were ordained Elders in the Apoſtles dayes by election, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.3, 4. the holy Ghoſt is given without hands to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, as alſo to the people, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.44.</p>
               <p>Extraordinary gifts were common to Paſtors and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but the calling of a Presbyter or Prieſt was either
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21240:25"/>of God and by God immediatly, or elſe of God and by man mediately, and this for Ordination, was alwayes the impoſition of the hands of the Apoſtles or Biſhops, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.15, 6, 17. <hi>Philip</hi> Preached and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized and converted <hi>Samaria,</hi> but had not the power to confirme or ordaine them Paſtors, therefore is ſent unto them from <hi>Ieruſalem, Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to impoſe hands and give the holy Ghoſt: the Biſhops the Apoſtles left to ſucceede them; had the power of Ordination, and every Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>byter had it not: and it was the he eſie of <hi>Aerius</hi> that denied Biſhops this p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erogative above others: That ſeate is not ſure, nor Ordination juſtifiable, that is not by a Biſhop, who is able to derive his ſucceſſion in that reſpect from the Apoſtles. <hi>Bell. de Eccl. lib.</hi> 4 <hi>cap.</hi> 8. ſaith truely, that an argument from ſucceſſion proves negative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt Schiſmatikes, but not affirmatively for Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, <hi>Adferri praecipue, ad probandum non eſſe Eccleſiam, ubi non eſt ſucceſſio, ex quo tamen non colligitur ibi neceſſario eſſe Eccleſiam ubi est ſucceſſio,</hi> there can be no viſible Church where there is no ſucceſſion from the chaires of the Apoſtles: But the Greeke Churches prove as good ſucceſſion this way as the Latine, and therefore both being ſuſpected for Doctrine, wee muſt have recourſe to that memorable faying in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. <hi>They continued ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastly in the Apoſtles Doctrin &amp; Fellowſhip &amp; in breaking of bread and in Prayer.</hi> Theſe notes will torment all our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries; <hi>Papiſts</hi> with Doctrine, <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> with the Apoſtles Fellowſhip, and both in breaking of bread, the one, becauſe they breake no bread in ſubſtance, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe they diſtribute meere bread. As they diſlike an Altar, ſo they diſlike to be within it, by denying com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Biſhops, and doing many things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. Prayers except they be private cannot pleaſe them, and Church prayers ſpecially at an Altar, they ſpit and ſpend their tongues in talking againſt them. They ſay we take Gods Name in vaine by adviſed repetitions, and remember not their owne iterations and ſudden
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21240:25"/>irruptions to be incident to vanitie. I have ſtood the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon the number, to ſhew us the courſe of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and muſt make haſte in the reſt, as not able in a ſhort Treatiſe to inſiſt fully on all our heads.</p>
               <p>Their names are Presbyters, contracted Prieſts, and we cannot abide the title of the holy Ghoſt, becauſe our times have polluted it; I will not be ſo nice as to name the child otherwiſe than it was firſt Chriſtened. Their offices are honourable, in waiting immediatly upon the Lambes Throne: their Ornaments are either a white veſture for the body, or crownes of gold for the head. They are no ordinary Prieſts, but of the chiefe ranke: <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his <hi>Panegyricke Oration</hi> diſcribes them to be cloathed like Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. It muſt needes be a Prieſts garment <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.4. and to him that will reade <hi>Euſebius</hi> and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> together it will prove a <hi>white Surpleſſe;</hi> or a white garment downe to the foote: He hath likewiſe this to make S. <hi>Iohn</hi> Hiſtoricall as well as myſticall to every mans meaning; the Prieſts in the Temple of <hi>Tyre,</hi> are ſaid to have upon their heads <hi>Caeleſtes gloriae coronas,</hi> crownes of heavenly glory. Order, is, that they begin the Church Service and end it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.9. muſt warily be read, leaſt we make the people goe before their Paſtors <hi>when they are about to give glory;</hi> then riſe the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from their ſeates and fall downe firſt. The Churches Service is performed by ſinging, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.8, 9. to the end. The Elders and the Saints about the throne are furniſhed with <hi>Harpes,</hi> and <hi>Vials,</hi> inſtruments of Muſicke and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodie, be they Voyces or other Organs of Gods praiſe, for I will preciſely determine nothing, their <hi>gold Vials</hi> are ſaid to be full of odors, and theſe odours to be prayers, a right ſervice in Gods houſe. Their ſong is a new ſong of the Lamb, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Lamb, with theſe joyne the holy Angells, and in divine ſtraines of the ſweeteſt muſique, ſound with a loud voyce in Gods eares &amp; as they end with bleſſing ſo all creatures like an <hi>Echo</hi> lay hold of that laſt word, &amp; ſay
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21240:26"/>bleſſing, &amp;c. Then conclude the Beaſts with a voyce as a thunderclappe, for ſo ſpeakes Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> of the word <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Elders end the ſervice as they began with proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for as that is before confeſſion, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10, 11. ſo it is after all ſervice, and the whole body is prepared, before that member the tongue take in hand to utter a word. Hee were impudent that would talke ſtanding with his God, and beginne to ſpeake before hee hath ſhewed his feare by falling downe to ſo great a Majeſtie as he ſeekes to ſerve, neither were it fit a man ſhould ſtand by and take his leave, as if two equalls were met (we neither come ſo into the preſence of out parents, neither doe we ſo depart from them) and ſhame our ſelves as if wee had met none in Gods Houſe better than our ſelves. The El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as they fall firſt, ſo they are found laſt in the like po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and ſo we leave them, and come to our third thing in Gods Houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21240:26"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Concerning the ſtandards of the people, and the gurd of Angells, that is the place of Lay-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and the attendance of holy Angells in Gods Houſe.</hi> Signa Sanctorum.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REv.</hi> 4.6, 7, 8, 9. The Standards, Enſignes, Banners, and Badges borne by the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſſe have ever beene the deſcription of a people gathered together before God to ſerve him, and I conceive the old and new Teſtament, in the accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof to have no other meaning and myſtery, though I know this is not made of it by many, both Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne and Ancient Divines. In one <hi>Pſalme</hi> Beaſts are Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems of the Campes and Companies both of the godly and ungodly. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.10. the word is <hi>Caiath</hi> or <hi>Caiah,</hi> which ſignifies the wild beaſts, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.24, 25. becauſe in them is the greateſt life and livelineſſe, and it is applied by <hi>David</hi> to Gods people, in whom there ought to be in the ſervice of God the greateſt ſpirit and life: Its likewiſe <hi>ve.</hi> 30. given to ſinners; and the <hi>Chaldee</hi> tranſlates it <hi>Armies</hi> of them, and further, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. its put for the troopes of the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> &amp; 1 <hi>Chro</hi> 11.15 the word <hi>Machanes</hi> is uſed for it, which every learned man knows to be a Campe or Leager, <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.2. <hi>Jacob</hi> calls the place where the Angells met him <hi>Mahanaim,</hi> two Hoaſts or Campes, for as <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> in the reare, and <hi>Eſau</hi> in the front came againſt Gods ſervant; ſo his bleſſed Angells came for him, and made two Campes to croſſe them both. In the ſong of ſongs it is concluded that the <hi>Shulamite</hi> ſhould convert to God as it were a double Army, tither of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> or as the children of the <hi>Iewes</hi> converted to their fathers,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21240:27"/>and the diſobedient to the wiſdome of the juſt. <hi>Can.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.17. I may hold my reſolution, and take the foure Beaſts for the congregation of the Gentiles, or all people that come in and encampe about the throne of the Lambe, and ſeates of his Miniſters, wee will conſider their names, number, orders, office, and actions.</p>
               <p>Names, <hi>Beaſts</hi> better as in <hi>Ezech.</hi> 1.5. <hi>living creatures</hi> of the moſt vigorous nature; <hi>Quatuor ſunt ſuperbi, vel qui emineant in mundo, Leo inter feras, Bos inter Iumenta, Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la inter volucres, &amp; Homo cui Deus ſupra omnes pulchritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem largitus eſt, ut omnibus imporaret, Schindler, pag.</hi> 266.<hi>d.</hi> Gods people ſhould be as couragious as <hi>Lyons,</hi> as patient in bearing their burdens as the <hi>Oxe</hi> is in labour, and ſubmitting to his maſters yoke. They ſhould quit themſelves as <hi>men</hi> in their beſt reaſon, and rule and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due their luſts to Gods Spirit. They ſhould like <hi>Eagles</hi> fore aloaft into the contemplation of divine things, and be ſpeedie in the diſpatch of all their buſineſſe, their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is foure, and that is from their quarters or campes, as they lie <hi>Eaſt, Weſt, North,</hi> and <hi>South.</hi> Their Catholicke concord and univerſall conſent in all things is divinely deſcribed by <hi>Ezechiel.</hi> Their <hi>faces,</hi> and <hi>wings, feete,</hi> and <hi>ſoles</hi> of their <hi>feete, wheeles</hi> and <hi>rings,</hi> are nothing elſe but their unanimous conſent in all things. Their faces are foure, and yet but one face in their aſpect, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>Foure had the face of a man, and the face of a Lyon, &amp;c.</hi> They were not as foure he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ads looking ſeverall wayes, but it ſeemes as one head faſhioned to forme foure faces, and all looking one way: when they looked <hi>Southward,</hi> they had all the face of a Man; when they looked <hi>Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> they had all the face of a Lyon; when they looked <hi>Weſtward,</hi> they had all the face of an Oxe; and when they looked <hi>Northward,</hi> they had all the face of an Eagle.</p>
               <p>Vniverſalitie and unitie in minde and motion is that which ought to be in Gods Saints: Their wings had the <hi>hands of a man under them,</hi> to ſhew that their high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21240:27"/>and foring into divine Myſteries was with humble and heartie readineſſe to doe the things they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. Their wheeles did carry them on all ſides in the ſame courſe, and the rings did unite them as one in motion, and they were full of eyes to direct them to the true end of all their actions: furthermore theſe foure Beaſts thus faſhioned and formed, to expreſſe the faith and fellowſhip of Gods people, and their univerſalitie to looke to all Regions in their Religion, and not Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matically to profeſſe one in a corner, or command all to looke into ſome diviſion or part; the holy Catholike Church is moſt univerſall, and binds us to all places where Ieſus Chriſt hath ſent his Goſpell, and this muſt alſo be added, that the foure beaſts are divided into twelve <hi>Tribes,</hi> and the order of three is in them all.</p>
               <p>To every beaſt three Tribes are allotted, and then the whole number is twelve, and this is a great myſterie and moſt certaine marke of a true Church in the <hi>Revelation, Rev.</hi> 7. The tribes are ſealed, and two for Idolatry ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the ſeale, as <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Ephraim,</hi> yet the number is made up, and twelve tribes are ſealed, and in each tribe twelve thouſand, and twelve times twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand is the number of Gods people, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. the crowne upon the head of the Church is 12. ſtars, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12.14. <hi>Twelve gates, twelve foundations:</hi> on the gates are written the twelve tribes, on the foundations the twelve Apoſtles, and what is all this but a Church conſtant in the Doctrine and Fellowſhip of the Apoſtles. Their order is ſtrangely deſcribed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.6. they are <hi>in the middeſt of the throne, and round about it,</hi> no circumference, but every point of it reſts upon the center. It was Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> joy, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5. to ſee the <hi>order</hi> and <hi>faith</hi> of that Church: <hi>faith</hi> plants a Church upon the foundation, and thats Chriſt; order keepes all the members from confuſion, and placeth them as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the body, that all may ſerve for the good of the whole. Their office is in their eyes and wings, and it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21240:28"/>ſeemes the one is outward, and the other inward, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. their wings and their workes are to be ſeene of men, but their eyes that muſt guide therein be within, and ſecret in themſelves, and muſt teach them, that Gods Service muſt be with underſtanding; God loves cheerefulneſſe in our obedience, and wiſedome in all our workes, their actions are to give glory unto God, and not to reſt night nor day in praiſes of his Name.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Castra Angelorum.</head>
                  <p>The laſt part is the inviſible attendance of Angells, and ſhewes the Majeſtie of God to be exceeding great; <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Angells are before the Throne,</hi> and theſe I take to be the Princes of Angells, and the millions of the reſt watch and ward, and worſhip with us our gracious Saviour. Our Church hath added; <hi>Therefore with Angells and Archangells, and with all the company of Heaven wee laud and magnifie thy glorious Name, and evermore, prayſing thee and ſaying, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Hoſts, Heaven and Earth are full of thy glory, Glory be to thee O Lord moſt high.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:21240:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Contayning an exhortation to conſtancie in the Doctrine, Fellowſhip, Sacraments, and Prayers of the Church,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Act. 2.42.</bibl>
               </head>
               <p>HE that will not be an <hi>Heretick</hi> and denie the truth, muſt continue ſtedfaſt in the Apoſtles doctrine, &amp; he that wil not be a <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> &amp; depart from the Church, muſt keepe himſelfe in the communion of the Apoſtles, that he may be partaker of the Altar and Prayers of the Church. Saint <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his Epiſtles very often makes the communion of the one to flow from the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with the other. Take away the <hi>Apoſtles fellowſhip,</hi> and you take away the <hi>breaking of bread,</hi> and prayer at the Lords Table: except there be a Prieſt within the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, the people are wholly without it. I ſay, it is Saint <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> his conſtant determination, that the people muſt ſo depend upon their Paſtours, that they doe nothing without them, <hi>Ep. ad Polycarpum,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, As nothing muſt be done without the minde of the Biſhop, ſo the Biſhop muſt do nothing without the minde of God.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles and Biſhops hee makes next to God in the Church, he acknowledgeth none above them, reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Eccleſia ſticall Miniſterie. <hi>Epiſt. ad Trall.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Be ſubject to the Biſhop, as to Chriſt, for he watcheth for you. He applyes the Apoſtles words, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. to the Biſhop, and defines him in the ſame Epiſtle, leſt we ſhould ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21240:29"/>his name to be common to all Paſtours, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; what is a Biſhop but one that bears ſway and autoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all others? <hi>Epiſt. ad Smyrnenſes,</hi> he ſayes thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, As in all the world there is none grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then God, ſo in the Church and Order Eccleſiaſticall, there is none greater then the Biſhop. The ſame Father exhorts in <hi>Epiſt. ad Epheſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The people ſhould concurre in their conſent to what their Biſhop teacheth them according to God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that they may concurre and accord in Gods minde: and again, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The people muſt live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods minde, and the Biſhop muſt be their guide ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. As in the Apoſtles dayes, the head of the Churches fellowſhip was from them, to which our Saviour added ſeventie Diſciples; ſo in the ſucceſſion, the Biſhop is the head and chiefe to which the Presbyters are added, and of them Saint <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſayes thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. be ſubject to the Presbyterie, as to the Apoſtles. This he explains after, when he makes a fuller narration. <hi>Epiſt. ad Trall.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The Biſhop is the type of him which is the father of all. Prieſts are the aſſeſſors with God &amp; the band of Apoſtles. The Apoſtles fellowſhip, as it was in the the 12 Apoſtles &amp; 70 Diſciples, ſo afterwards it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in Biſhops and Presbyters, and as the Apoſtles had commited unto them the calling of all ordinary Paſtours, and correction of all mens manners, that is, God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them to ordaine and cenſure, and without them the ſeventie could not execute any ſuch power: So the Biſhops above all other Paſtors have this power, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them it cannot be executed by any inferior Miniſter.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21240:29"/>And I never read teſtimonie in the Word of God, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ancient Writer to the contrary. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> decreed the Excommunication of the inceſtuous perſon, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> the execution thereof, &amp; reprehended them for their neglect. As we are to receive our doctrine from the Apoſtles, ſo our fellowſhip, and all proofe of ſucceſſion in the Miniſtery is taken from thence, <hi>Tertull. lib. de praeſcript. c.</hi> 32. <hi>Evolvant ordinem Epiſcoporum ſuorum, it a per ſucceſſiones ab initio decur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem, ut primus ille Epiſcopus aliquem ex Apoſtolis vel Apoſtolicis viris, qui tamen cum Apoſtolis perſeverarit, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerint auctorem &amp; anteceſſorem hoc enim medo Eccleſiae Apoſtolicae cenſus ſuos deferunt: ſic</hi> Smyrnaeorum <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia habens</hi> Polycarpum <hi>à</hi> Ioanne <hi>collocatumrefert, ſicut Romanorum</hi> Clementem <hi>à</hi> Petro <hi>ordinatum edit.</hi> Let them examine the order of their Biſhops, that ſo hath held by ſucceſſion from the beginning, that, that firſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop might have for his authour and predeceſſour, ſome of the Apoſtles or Apoſtolicall men, yet ſuch as have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevered with the Apoſtles, for ſo the Apoſtolicall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches gave their Suffrages. So he relates of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> where <hi>Polycarpe</hi> was placed by Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> and ſhewes the like of <hi>Clement,</hi> ordained by <hi>Peter</hi> for the Romanes. <hi>Cyprianus l.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 20. or <hi>Pamelii</hi> 42. <hi>labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare debemus, ut unitatem à Domino &amp; per Apoſtolos no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſucceſſoribus traditam obtinere curemus,</hi> we ought to labour, that the unitie from the Lord, and by the Apoſtles to us his ſucceſſours given, through our care might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. <hi>S. Auguſtine in Pſal.</hi> 44. <hi>quid eſt, pro patribus tuis nati ſunt tobi filii, patres miſſi ſunt Apoſtoli, pro Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis filii nati ſunt tibi, conſtituti ſunt Epiſcopi? Hodie enim Epiſcopi, quiſunt per totum mundum, unde natiſunt, Ipſa Eccleſia patres illos appellat, ipſaillos genuit, &amp; ipſaillos conſtituit in ſedibus patrum.</hi> What means this, in ſtead of fathers, ſonnes are borne to thee? the Apoſtles are ſent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21240:30"/>for Apoſtles ſonnes are ſent to thee, Biſhops are conſtituted; for the Biſhops at this time, that are through all the World, whence are they born? the Church it ſelfe calls them fathers that begot them, and that conſtituted them in the ſeats of the fathers; many moe ſuch paſſages might be cited and ſent both to <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſome other Churches as citations, nay, as ſentences of condemnation for two errors, both contrary to this truth, as they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo contrary one to another; and agree in nothing but falſhood; firſt, <hi>Bellarmine l.</hi> 4. <hi>de Pontific. cap.</hi> 25. ſayes thus, <hi>Magnum eſt diſcrimen inter ſucceſſionem</hi> Petri <hi>&amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum Apoſtolorum. Nam Romanus Pontifex propree ſuccedit</hi> Petro, <hi>non ut Apoſtolo, ſed ut paſtori ordinario to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Eccleſiae: at Epiſcopi non ſuccedunt proprtè Apoſtolis; quoniam, Apoſtoli non fuerunt ordinarii ſed extraordinarii paſtores, quibus non ſuceeditur, niſi improprié.</hi> But God appointed his Apoſtles, ſuch as ſhould be ſucceeded: for how otherwiſe is his promiſe made good of being with them to the worlds end? Others to avoid the Pope and all Biſhops, ſay this fellowſhip may come from all Paſtors, and that they have power to ordain, nay, ſome are ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, that they ſtick not to ſay, Paſtors maybe made by the people, and Magiſtrates may ſet up Miniſters, and never be beholding to <hi>Rome,</hi> or any Biſhops or Paſtours that were ever ordained by them. Saint <hi>Ignatius Epiſt. ad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, obeying the Biſhop and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery with immoveable and ſtedfaſt minde, breaking one bread, &amp;c. He ſhews plainly that breaking of bread muſt follow our undivided fellowſhip from the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſours: and ſurely how can we have the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments duly adminiſtred, if wee be not truly informed of our Paſtours calling, and the comming of it from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles?</p>
               <p>Let mee exhort all good Chriſtians to keepe cloſe to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21240:30"/>theſe notes of the Church; firſt, ſound Doctrine, which the Apoſtles have only delivered. Secondly, an holy fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, fetched from the Apoſtles, and kept by the faithfull in all obedience to their Biſhops as the chiefe of Paſtours, and the Presbyters, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Epiſt. ad Trall.</hi> as his <hi>conſiliarii &amp; aſſeſſores,</hi> engliſh it as you will, ſo you erre no more in your baſe account of Biſhops. What hath not <hi>Rome</hi> made offenſive to vulgar eares? the name of a Biſhop, Prieſt, Altar, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and all Church-ſervice is ſet at nought, and wee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre to heare of veneiable antiquitie, its to ſmall purpoſe to preſſe any thing upon them that have ſworn to believe nothing but their own novelties, and late inventions of diſcontented perſons ſet on foot to trouble the peace and quiet of our Church, which (I beleeve) holds in the moſt holy manner the Doctrine, Fellowſhip, Altar, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers expreſſed, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42.</p>
               <p>Storme not at the word Altar, for breaking of bread cannot be without it in that ſenſe which is ſo often incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in the Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and think no man can be ignorant, that will not wilfully blinde his eyes with prejudice to an Altar, and rather make it any thing then an holy Table: ſurely from fellow ſhip with Biſhops he concludes his Altar, as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> does breaking of bread from fellowſhip with the Apoſtles. I would wiſh the ſeparation of our times to take need leſt to avoid Pope ry, they part with puritie it ſelfe, and do not ſo much find as forſake what they ſeek for, if they take not miniſterie from us, they have none. Then they can have no Baptiſm, break no bread, and where will they finde the marks and notes of their Church, if they brand ours for none of Gods? our Doctrine, Fellowſhip, Altar, and Prayers, will find footing, when I feare they will faile in all, if they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeus in any. May I conclude, &amp; not be thought to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? for I profeſſe what I have ſaid hath ever been my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that Biſhops are by divine inſtitution.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21240:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The Cauſe and Cure of all our Contentions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Vnitie in the Church is the path of peace, which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Sectaries diſturbe in a contrary courſe. The one miſplacing the head, the other the feet, and both ſet them where they ſhould not. The Papiſts place their Popc, where they ſhould place all Biſhops, and Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſeeke that in the feet which is onely to be found in the head. Saint <hi>Cyprian de unitate Eccleſ.</hi> compares the univerſall power and juriſdiction of Biſhops to an head, which derives all the vertue to the bodie. To a root which feeds and fils all the branches. To a fountain from which flow all ſtreams. To the Sunne that ſends forth all rayes and beames, &amp;c. This head, root, fountain, and Sun, the Papiſts make their Pope, &amp; all Biſhops but members, branches, ſtreames, and beames of him. <hi>Ab uno Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu tanquam ab uno capite, radice, fonte, ſole oriuntur om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Epiſcapi, &amp; hujus Epiſcopatus a ſingulis in ſolidum pars tenetur. A ſingulis in ſolidum,</hi> every Biſhop holds wholly for his part whatſoever is in the whole. The head, root, fountain and Sun are ſimilar and alike in all the members. The ſame vertue is in one Biſhop that is in all Biſhops, and the body being univocall, hath but one eſſence in al the parts of it. Order, juriſdiction is the ſame, and nothing heterogeneall, but the Popes challenge to take all to himſelfe, and make Biſhops ſtand to his cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie for their calling and power, as if all the Sea were in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21240:31"/>
                  <hi>Tyber,</hi> or the whole Sunne in the Romane Sphere, the root in one branch, and all the vertue of the head in one member. Sectaries are as ſenſleſſe that take off the head to give life to the feet: raiſe up the root, that the branches may flouriſh. Cut off the fountain, that the ſtreames may flow, and remove the Sun out of its Orbe, that they may enjoy the light. Theſe be our diſeaſes, whoſe cauſes and cure we are now to ſeeke out, and hope it will helpe us to recover our miſery.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe I may reduce all the cauſes to two heads, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie and Ignorance, Envie of the perſons, Ignorance of the calling of our Biſhops. Their perſons and practices are ſo hated, that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> muſt be unbiſhoped for their ſakes. We imagine corruptions in Biſhops, and caſt ſuch eyes of diſcontent upon them, that we cannot abide to heare of their calling. I am confident, till that be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, our contentions will never ceaſe. They are the words of holy <hi>Ignatius,</hi> breathing with the ſweet ſpirit, that was in the beloved Diſciple, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, fly the diviſion of unitie, his arguments which are as medicines to cure the diſeaſe are foure, <hi>Epiſt. ad Philad.</hi> Firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one faith to be beleeved of all. Secondly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one predication of the ſame as an effectuall meanes. Thirdly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one Euchariſt to ſeale it, wherein are many unities to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us from diviſion. Firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one fleſh of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt given for us. Secondly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one bloud ſhed for us. Thirdly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one bread viſibly broken to us. Fourthly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one cup diſtributed to us all. Fiftly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one Altar or Table, where we communicate. The laſt argument, is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one Biſhop together with the Presbytery and Deacons. This laft unitie being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, diſturbes all the reſt, and becauſe all the ſpite is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſhops wherein lyes the Churches unitie, we
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21240:32"/>will vindicate the truth thereof, and prove plainly, that Biſhops as the beſt inſtruments, derive all power and peace to the Church, and that without them no unitie can poſſibly in all the reſt be imagined or mayntained.</p>
               <p>We will begin with the mayn text, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12. There is a double calling for a threefold end. Firſt, extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, in <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts.</hi> Secondly, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in <hi>Paſtors and Teachers.</hi> Vpon theſe two hangs the perfection of the Saints, work of the Miniſtery, and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the univerſall Church. In the firſt wee have that calling which is of God, and by God alone. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, that which is alſo of God, but by man, and here we muſt inquire by what men? the Scripture reſolves us, by the Apoſtles, and by no others; and therfore <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> could be no Evangeliſts for two reaſons: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not called immediatly of God and by God, but of God by man: and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, hee ordained <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. and no queſtion, the ſame is to be ſaid of <hi>Titus.</hi> Secondly, both theſe ordained o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which was effected by no extraordinary perſons before them ſince the Apoſtles. The objection is, that <hi>Timothy</hi> is bidden <hi>doe the work of an Evangeliſt,</hi> and therefore is one of their number. By this reaſon I muſt reckon alſo the foure Evangeliſts, and reduce them to the ſame order, and ſo confound Apoſtles and Evangeliſts. A cleere diſtinction will remedie this confuſion. Firſt, ſome Evangeliſts were writers of the Goſpel. Secondly, others Preachers of it, and both theſe are ſo called from the object of their imployment, and not from the author of their calling. We muſt therefore finde out in the third place Evangeliſts by calling, ſuch as was <hi>Philip, Acts</hi> 21.8. who being compared with the ſeventy, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.1. ſeemes to be an example of that calling. Firſt, they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, ſo did <hi>Philip.</hi> Secondly, they wrought miracles, ſo did <hi>Philip.</hi> Thirdly, they went before Chriſt to make
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21240:32"/>way for him, and his Miniſtery, ſo did <hi>Philip</hi> before the Apoſtles, as will appeare, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.5. and not onely hee, but many more, <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. which Chriſt had called before his death, of the ſeventy, the Apoſtles remayning at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Verſe</hi> 1. which followed <hi>Philip,</hi> when they heard of his ſucceſſe, <hi>Verſe</hi> 14. and ordained Paſtours where he had begun the Goſpel, <hi>Verſe</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>This immediate power to ordain, Chriſt gave his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and by ordinary Paſtours they are ſucceeded, and not by extraordinary, and <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> are exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſo is <hi>Epaphras Coloſ.</hi> 4.12. who was one of <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> when he was at <hi>Rome,</hi> for it is not following of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles that makes men <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> or every abſence, that denies them to be Biſhops. In <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> wee may conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture that <hi>Epaphras</hi> was Biſhop of that place, and had <hi>Laodicea</hi> and <hi>Hierapolis</hi> adjoyned unto it, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Archippus</hi> may be counted for the Presbyter with the Biſhop, and <hi>Philemon,</hi> in whoſe houſe he was the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles him in a manner, as <hi>Ignatius</hi> did the Deacons in his time, σύνεργος, fellow-labourer, σύνδουλος, fellow-ſervant, for ſuch work together in their Maſters buſineſſe. This order being obſerved, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Biſhops continue the ſucceſſion, and without the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is none in the Church. In theſe two Ieſus Chriſt immediatly communicates his power of the Keyes to the Church, and none receive it ordinarily but from ſome one of them. The Pope abuſeth all Biſhops to fetch them under his power. The people prophane Gods ordinance when they appoint Paſtours. We muſt confine our ſelves to theſe two heads, or elſe we miſſe Chriſts order, and this is not my conjecture, but the conceit of antiquitie, and by modern Divines is brought againſt the Popes u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation above Biſhops.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> in the Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>neque quiſquam noſtrum, Epiſcopum ſe eſſe Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coporum
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21240:33"/>conſtituit, aut tyrannico terrore ad obſequendi neceſſitatem collegas ſuos adigit.</hi> The Monarchie of one Biſhop in the univerſall Church is a plain tyranny, and ſo is a Presbytery in every Pariſh, where there is no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die as well againſt the popular as papall juriſdiction. If the Pope infect the Church it muſt needs periſh, becauſe there is no power above him, ſo muſt the Pariſh, for none can helpe it, being ſo independent in it ſelfe, and abſolute from the command of all others: both theſe take away all libertie of calling Councels, and are uncontrouleable in their own wayes. This cannot be of God, to leave his Church deſperate of meanes to helpe it. Betweene both there is a middle way, and that is to have the Churches power in the hands of many, ſo that one may helpe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Councell, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. the Apoſtles as heads with the Elders, meet in conſultation &amp; determine what is beſt for the Churches in <hi>Antioch, Syria,</hi> and <hi>Cilicia, V.</hi> 23 and wiſely apply the remedie according to the diſeaſe, for it ſeemes to ſome good Divines, that the act involves no more then are mentioned in it, and that <hi>Corinth</hi> and other Churches were not tyed by this Canon: but might eat of meats ſacrificed to Idols, and onely were to uſe charitie and diſcretion at ſuch times as it might offend the weake Apoſtles and Elders, conſider of the matter, <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. diſpute and determine it, and diſperſe abroad the Decree to be obſerved of thoſe Churches that are ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in it. A cleare and evident truth. How the Apoſtles attempted to do nothing without conſent. Its a true rule, that no one man makes Canons for all Churches, &amp; there was never any Biſhop ſave the Pope that challenged all power: but as men moſt peaceably ſought to governe after the divine Canon, and approved Cuſtoms &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of Gods Church. No Biſhop makes Lawes, but takes (as he ought) the ſole power to ſee them executed; for if
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21240:33"/>God truſt them with his power to ſee it executed, ſhall the Church diſtruſt them with her Councels?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would help the Pope into his chaire by this poore ſhift. Biſhops are abſolute in their Dioceſes, and have none above them, therefore is the Pope ſo in all the World. An Argument of an ill conſequent, and contrary to Chriſt and his Church. To Chriſt Ieſus, to deprive him of his Monarchie, and order of ruling, who began with many, and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. makes mention of all his officers in the plurall number, and in no ranke can wee thruſt in one to be above al; when the Apoſtles were above the 70 they were many, and it is but a miſerable begging of the queſtion to bring in Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> as the head of all the reſt. Wee finde that in a multitude, yet well ordered, and ſee in the extraordinary calling a number of Apoſtles above all the reſt, and in the ordinary we finde numbers of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and teachers, yet not confuſed, as to ſet them all in one and the ſame indifferencie and equalitie of place &amp; dignitie, for this would bring the Church to an anarchie; for where there is no order, there is juſt conteſtation that no man is bound to any obedience to another, and whiles all ſtrive to be equall, the Church will never ceaſe to quarrell. I muſt therefore thinke the tyranny of one and all alike; for what the Pope pleads to have none above him, ſo all plead the ſame that they will have none above themſelves. To ſay none are above Biſhops, makes them equall, and ſuch an equalitie ſtands with the Churches peace, and without it, it will never be obtained or mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus eſt Epiſcopatus, cujus à ſingulis in ſolidum pars tenetur. Cyprian. de unitat. Eccleſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I produce my teſtimonies for them, three mayn objections would be cleered. Firſt, From their election, they may be choſen of others. Secondly, they may chooſe others to ordain with them or for them. Thirdly, they are the Churches invention. Others may chooſe them,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21240:34"/>Saint <hi>Ignat. Epiſt. ad Philadel.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. It behoves you of <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> as the Church of God to chooſe a Biſhop, and Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> for all Prieſts, <hi>Plebs maximè habet poteſtatem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendi dignos ſacerdotes, vel indignos recuſaudi, Concil. African. apud Cyprian. Epiſt,</hi> 68. If the people may chuſe Biſhops and Prieſts, their power is not ſo immediatly of God, but the Church may intercede and act a part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and them, as it did, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.2.3. Saint <hi>Ignatius</hi> will give us light and leading to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere ſufficiently all theſe teſtimonies. It behoves you of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> to chooſe a Biſhop for the Church of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> in <hi>Syria, ut obeat legationem Dei, &amp; concedatur il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis in eundem locum congregatis, etiam glorifioare nomen Dei,</hi> that he may undertake Gods delegation, and that the people of the ſame place may congregate, and give God his due glory. Without a Biſhop to order the Church aſſemblies, they are meere conventicles and unlawfull meetings. Here by the way obſerve that the Father ſpeake of ſuch helpe as one Church may and ought to afford an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. <hi>Annunciatum eſt mihi Eccleſiam Antiochenam eſſe pacatam:</hi> it is reported unto me, that the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> is quiet and peaceable, and needs your help, that enjoy a worthy Biſhop, and I would wiſh you to doe as Gods Churches have alwayes done, <hi>ut ſemper ſecerunt proximae Eccleſiae, quorum aliae miſere Epiſcopos, nonnullae verò presbyteros &amp; Diaconos,</hi> that the next Churches ſome of them have ſupplyed their neighbour Churches with Biſhops, others with Prieſts and Deacons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> outreacheth and ſtraineth this teſtimonie upon the largeſt laſt, and helps to ſtretch it with her teeth for the Pope, that hee ought to chooſe all Biſhops for the Churches. With his leave, the words ſerve for any Biſhop with his Church to helpe others to able men that want them, and for our Noveliſts they may not once name this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21240:34"/>text, that will chooſe for themſelves, and ſuffer no others to meddle with their right, when all Churches have, &amp; ought to have a common right one in another. For the words of Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> they may be expounded that the people being peaceable as it was with the Church of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> and keeping concord amongſt themſelves they may then with one conſent uſe all their power to gaine worthy Prieſts, and ingage it to the uttermoſt to oppoſe them that are wicked and unworthy, and their teſtimony is to be heard of their betters. The Church ſeparates two, and God makes choice of one, ſeven honeſt men are looked out of the ſocietie of Saints, and appointed by the Apoſtles to the buſineſſe of the Church, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> are ſeparated by the Church to a ſpeciall work, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to them by the holy Ghoſt. Let the people on Gods name in theſe peaceable wayes walke with the Church, and for the Church, and I know none will condemne them: but they are to know all theſe elections are not of the eſſence of a Biſhop, for hee may be ſo when hee is ſent from one Church to another, and therfore to ſpeake diſtinctly, and avoid confuſion, Ordination belongs to a Prieſt, Conſecration to a Biſhop, and Tranſlation is when he is removed from one place to another. Theſe three are the formes of the Church, and Rites ſhe uſeth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe her ſelfe: but the Epiſcopall power is that which God gives unto them, whom hee uſeth as his immediate means to convey it to the whole Church.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond objection, that Biſhops ordaine with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and by others is eaſily anſwered in <hi>Timothy,</hi> that he was ordained by the hands of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and may be the hands of the Presbytery, that is, of others that joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him, or it may be the office hee received by S. <hi>Pauls</hi> hands alone. The queſtion is not whether Prieſts may joyne with the Biſhop: but whether they may do it alone without the Biſhop. There is ſome thing ſaid for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21240:35"/>
                  <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> or rurall Biſhops that they have ordained, which were unlawfull, if ordination were ſolely Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall. I anſwer, what the Biſhop may doe by deputation is nothing to my diſputation. I ſpeak of Gods order, and that which is divine, of the humane Laws of the Church, and what power Biſhops have to depute others I leave to them. I look upon that which I conceive to be Gods appointment, and the conſtant courſe of the Scriptures, which ſignifies unto us that either the Apoſtles, or ſuch as <hi>Timothie</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> ordained, and not one word of any Evangeliſt or Prophet, or of all Paſtours, but ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ones ſelected by the Apoſtles before their death. So <hi>Timothie</hi> ordained as an Evangeliſt, and you at once af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme two untruths, 1 that <hi>Timothie</hi> was extraordinarily called, and ſecondly, that ſuch an one being none of the Apoſtles number might ordaine: <hi>Timothie</hi> was made a Miniſter by impoſition of hands, and to <hi>Timothie</hi> was committed the power to impoſe hands upon others: but both are arguments againſt his extraordinary calling, and hee that makes Evangeliſts or Prophets by impoſition of hands ſayes that which no word of holy Scripture will warrant him, either by one example or precept in all the new Teſtament.</p>
               <p>The third objection is, that Biſhops are the Churches invention, <hi>in Schiſmatis remedium.</hi> I am glad, they that like not of Biſhops to be of God, will confeſſe them to be of men, for ſo good an end, and it ſhewes what wee have ſaid to be abſolutely true, that without Biſhops, the Church muſt needs be filled with faction, and ſure I am, the quarrell with them is the cauſe of all our doleful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and grievous complaints, and if men could work them out, and have their wils, it would not be, <hi>So many men, ſo many mindes,</hi> but millions of miſchiefe and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to this our Nation. Its well they ſee ſuch wiſdome in the neceſſitie of Biſhops: but is not the originall dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21240:35"/>to cenſure Gods Providence of defect, and mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of Idolatry. To ſay God provided not for Schiſme is to mee a ſecret Atheiſme, and checke to him that better ſees what the Church needeth, then to leave it in ſo mayne a matter to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie and pietie of men. Againe, the remedie is worſe then the diſeaſe, and of deſperate cure to them that call all humane inventions in queſtion for Idolatry. I hope a neceſſary means to prevent diviſion in Religion is a ſpeciall ordinance of God, and to make it humane is worſe in my thoughts then to make it divine.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> is the moſt welcome autour they have, and yet, <hi>contra Luciferan.</hi> hee ſayes, the Church conſiſts of many degrees, and makes the higheſt end in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope, and <hi>Dionyſius Eccleſiaſt. Hierarch. c.</hi> 5. affirmes not of one, but of all Biſhops, that <hi>immediatè in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum terminantur:</hi> and the aforeſaid authour, <hi>ad Eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grium,</hi> ſayes, <hi>ſummum tenent locum,</hi> and Saint <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. Epiſt.</hi> 65. <hi>Pamel. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 9. <hi>Epiſcopi omnes Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolorum ſunt ſucceſſores.</hi> It were eaſie to multiply au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torities that ſpeake home in this buſineſſe. Saint <hi>Ignat. Epiſt. ad Smyru. Laici ſubjecti ſunto Diaconis. Diaconi Presbyteris, Presbyteri Epiſcopo, Epiſcopus Chriſto, ut Chriſtus patri.</hi> The ſubordination and ſucceſſion is full, Lay-men muſt ſubmit to the Deacons, the Deacons to the Prieſts, the Prieſts to the Biſhop, the Biſhop to Ieſus Chriſt, as Ieſus Chriſt to his Father. <hi>Epiſt. ad Magn. ut praeſideant Epiſcopi loco Dei, &amp; Presbyteri, loco conceſſus Apoſtolici, &amp;c.</hi> Biſhops are placed in Gods ſtead, Prieſts accompany them as the Apoſtles did Chriſt. Hee called them to worke with him, and ſo Biſhops call Prieſts to preach the Goſpel, and propagate the faith with them. We muſt lay the compariſon thus, as the Apoſtles were to Chriſt, ſo are Prieſts to Biſhops. The ſimilitude holds in the ſubordination, not in the equalitie, as if either Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21240:36"/>were equall to Chriſt, or Prieſts to the Apoſtles, but the accommodation of the ſenſe muſt be as the Autor means it in the order of things, and not the juriſdiction; for here the diſtinction will hold and helpe us, that is by Papiſts abſurdly applyed to the Apoſtles, to make them equall in the one, but not in the other: when wee are certain of them, that order, and juriſdiction is the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſiodorus de officiis Eccleſiaſticis l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. explaines ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what Biſhops and Prieſts hold in common, and what is proper to the one above the other. <hi>His ſicut Epiſcopis, dispenſatio miniſteriorum Dei commiſſa eſt, praeſunt enim Eccleſiis Chriſti, &amp; in confectione divini corporis &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis conſortes cum Epiſcopis ſunt: ſimiliter &amp; in doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na populi, &amp; in officio praedicandi: ſed ſola propter autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſummo ſacerdoti Clericorum ordinatio, &amp; conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio reſervata eſt.</hi> Chryſoſtome <hi>ſola ordinatione Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teros Epiſcopi ſuperant, atque hoc tantum pluſquam Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri habere videntur.</hi> Saint <hi>Hier. in Epiſt. ad Euagrium, quid facit Epiſcopus, excepta ordinatione, quod non faciat Presbyter,</hi> Saint <hi>Cyprian. Epiſt.</hi> 65. ſayes thus, <hi>Dominus, Apoſtolos, &amp; Epiſcopos elegit, Apoſtoli elegerunt Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</hi> He vindicates the Biſhops power from a proud and inſolent Deacon, and calls him to conſider that there is ſome thing between his calling and a Biſhops, as having men and not Chriſt immediately to appoint him. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zian. in Apolog. Fug.</hi> hath this ſhort ſaying, <hi>Epiſcopi</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Chriſti in ſacerdotio collegae ſunt,</hi> they are Chriſts companions in the Prieſthood, <hi>Aug. in lib. Quaeſt. ex vet. teſt. c.</hi> 35. <hi>Epiſcopus Chriſti imaginem habet, ut rex Dei. Ambr. in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>Epiſcopus habet perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Chriſti, &amp; eſt vicarius Dei.</hi> I will end with two of their own, that would draw from Biſhops to the Pope, that which is not his due, which theſe are forced to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alphon. de Caeſtr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 24. <hi>de juſta Haeret, punit.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetani
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21240:36"/>
                  <hi>ſententia eſt ipſamet falſitate falſior, &amp; eſt contra ſententiam omnium ſacrorum doctorum, nam etſi ritus conſecrandi Epiſcopi eſt ab Eccleſia, tamen poteſtas Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi, conceſſa illies a Deo eſt, non ab homine.</hi> The Church may conſecrate Biſhops, but it hath no power to confer their autoritie, which is given them of God, and not of man. <hi>Caeſar Baronius in Annal. Anno</hi> 58. ſayes it is moſt certain, that the Apoſtles had their dignitie of Chriſt, and therfore Biſhops that ſucceed them muſt needs have it from the ſame fountain.</p>
               <p>I hope, I may now conclude, that Biſhops as they are holy in calling, ſo they ought to be honourable in our account, and that our cauſes of contention ought to ceaſe, for certainly, as long as we imagine their vocation to be humane, and their actions inhumane, ſo long wee muſt needs live at diſtance, and true devotion will be devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up with damnable practices, of which our age is full. If <hi>Iſmaels</hi> tongue be perſecution, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. then I believe they are perſecuted which ſeeme to perſecute others. Never did any man, convicted, go from the ſeat of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without complaint, and exclamation of accuſers, witneſſes, or judges. Men <hi>ſhall gnaſh their teeth</hi> againſt the moſt righteous judge and revenge that with words, or an irefull countenance, which they cannot compaſſe by their power. I profeſſe its difficult to diſpute with Adverſaries, and not to anſwere them with their owne language.</p>
               <p>Deſpiſers of Dominions, and ill ſpeakers of Dignities are compared, <hi>Iude, verſe</hi> 9. to the Devill, who defends himſelfe by lyes, and all manner of lewdneſſe: but thoſe that will diſpute with theſe, muſt be like <hi>Michael the Arch-angell,</hi> not ſo much as to dare to bring railing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations againſt any, but <hi>ſay, the Lord rebuke them</hi> that ſpeake evill of thoſe things they know not, and in the which they corrupt themſelves like bruit beaſts, who are
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21240:37"/>inraged if any man doe ſtirre them never ſo little. Saint <hi>Aug. de doct. Chriſt.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 24, <hi>dicat ſapienter, quod non poteſt eloquenter:</hi> it is better be wiſe, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loquent in this way, and it is true wiſdome that knowes how to preſerve truth and peace together. This will carry no water about it to quench zeale, but onely ſo much as may ſprinkle it that it may burn the better within compaſſe, &amp; not fire the houſe, which is intended but to warm, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours ſhould have the leſſe work, if men would walke by this rule. I know ſcandall will hardly be eſcaped in the beſt intentions, we have to others. But S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſhall anſwer for me, <hi>Si de veritate ſcandalum ſumitur, uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liùs permittitur naſci ſcandalum, quam relinquatur veritas,</hi> if any man will be offended with the truth, its more profitable to permit the ſcandall, then part with the truth. <hi>Conſider what is ſaid,</hi> without paſſion, <hi>and the Lord give us underſtanding in all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:21240:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Touching ſome additions to illuſtrate ſome former paſſages, and give ſatisfaction in the uſe of a day to God, a place for God, and his bleſſed Name to be adored above all names.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IGnorance of antiquitie breeds the errours of noveltie, Its a readie, but a moſt rude anſwere to an argument from authoritie, <hi>I care not a button for a Father,</hi> I feare not to finde the forme of Gods ſervice better in <hi>I.C.</hi> and <hi>T.C.</hi> then in holy <hi>Ignatius</hi> which lived in the times of the Apoſtles. <hi>Liturgies</hi> they like not, all their learning lyes in themſelves, and they are able in publique to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the forme of prayer before they have made it, and if it were not new in the motion of their own private ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, it would ſpend it ſelfe and languiſh in the dead letter of a publick and common practiſed pattern.</p>
               <p>For Doctrine and Diſcipline they will truſt nothing but the Scriptures, and by them they will be tried, but then they muſt expound them by their private interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, leſt the publique prove poyſoned with humane inventions. Thus wee condemne, and then contemne, judge, and then deſpiſe our betters, For my part, I eſteem one bleſſed <hi>Ignatius</hi> above all moderne Writers for my warrant in the ſervice and ſocietie of the Saints, If they ſhould all ſet themſelves againſt him in the government of the Church by Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, and the communion of the people with them at the holy Altar, I
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21240:38"/>had rather reſt upon him for a conſtant and ocular wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then wreſt and wring all to the new forme of this laſt age.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles</hi> may be an hiſtorie of the Churches plantation for ſome twenty yeares, but Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> that ſaw Churches planted and eſtabliſhed, might well ſay more, and ſet down the exact pattern in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie written thirty or forty years afterwards, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Ignatius</hi> living with Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> might ſpeake that plainly which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> expreſſed myſtically, yet by his alluſion to the Church of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> might let us ſee our ſurrogation into their place, and caſt the forme after that faſhion, then the which there could not be a better, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting apart the types which were fulfilled in Chriſt, for beſides them, we might ſerve God upon our holy dayes, as they did upon theirs, in our holy places, as they did in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heirs.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>John</hi> reſembled our place of Majeſtie by theirs, our place of Miniſtery by theirs, our place of Auditory by theirs. They kept one day in a week, ſo do we, they kept Feaſts and Feſtivals, ſo doe we, as Eaſter, Pentecoſt, the Nativitie of Chriſt, &amp;c. We are Chriſtians in that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were <hi>Iews,</hi> and ſhew that their ſhadows are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into perfect light, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.1. we have that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our feet which was the crown of their head, and that upon our whole bodie which they looked for. The Sun the Embleme of our Church, and the meaſure of our time and ſervice. Their Feaſts were all lunary, ours ſolarie, and moneths in Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> are appoſed to days and yeers, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.23. &amp; 12.6.14. &amp; 13.5. and makes the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betweene a true and falſe company of Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>I ſay the Sunne is a great ceremony in the Chriſtian Church, and ſo is the Eaſt where it riſeth, as may be ſeen in the ſolemnitie of Baptiſme, which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. Baptiſme is the interrogation of a good
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21240:38"/>conſcience, and ſaveth the Church from the floud of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacie, as <hi>Noahs Arke</hi> did eight perſons from drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>Revel.</hi> 7.1. The foure Winds that ſhake the foure corners of the earth are barbarous wars, ſometimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to great and mighty waters, ſometimes to terrible and tempeſtuous windes, theſe caſt downe Kingdomes, and cauſe confuſion, and there is nothing that can ſtand theſe blaſts but the ſealed ſocietie, and Baptiſme well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, will reach the meaning, as being both the ſeale of our ſervice and ſafety with God, if we keepe it, it will keepe us, and bind as well God to us for ſafetie, as it binds us to him in a ſervice as a maſter.</p>
               <p>The making of our vow in Baptiſme, is wonderfull ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne, if wee ſearch out the ceremonies of ſpeaking and ſtanding at the Font or Fountaine to be baptized. The interrogation is Saint <hi>Peters</hi> expreſſion, and it was made to the conſcience of the believer, <hi>abrenuncias? abrenuncio. Credis? Credo,</hi> more largely thus in the anſwere of the party to be baptized, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. I disband my ſelfe from thee (O Satan) and from all thy Angels Autors of Idolatry, &amp; I do bid a farewell <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. to all thy mediators for me to thee, as a deceitfull God, and I utterly abhorre all thy pomps and vaine ſervices, &amp;c. Hereby the way underſtand how our Ancients made Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Playes, the renunciation of Baptiſme, and moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to all Chriſtians, becauſe they were ſervices to the dead, and helliſh honours to the infernall fiends, foes to Chriſt Ieſus, and furtherers of all Idolatry againſt him. The Chriſtians abrenunciation ſhould be remembred as the feale of his ſervice and ſafety, if hee returne againe to falſe Mediatours, hee loſeth the benefit of his Baptiſme, and becomes, as it were another mans ſervant, and ſeeks ſafety from another maſter.</p>
               <p>Having made his renunciation, he begins again, and ſayes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I binde my ſelfe, and binde my ſelfe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21240:39"/>for ever to thee, ô Chriſt, as my ſole Redeemer and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, and will gaine God, or go to God by no other, but thy ſelfe, and I believe, &amp;c. reade but the Churches Catechiſme, and the Churches Baptiſme, and wee ſhall finde Saint <hi>Peters</hi> interrogation, and the anſwere of a good conſcience made by the party to be baptized.</p>
               <p>The ſtanding will ſtirre more the coals of contention, but I cannot helpe it, to relate to a reaſonable man, what may well be received. In the abrenunciation of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, the partie was to look the Devill in the face, and ſet it <hi>Weſtward</hi> towards the Devils throne, or his Idoll and Altar, and teſtifie his defiance, and departure from him, and to ſpit at him in token of great deteſtation, <hi>Fie, get thee hence, what have I to do with Idols,</hi> pomps and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of Satan? This ceremonie ended he turns his back upon the enemy, and looks into the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and earneſtly vowes himſelfe to Chriſt, and from hence followes the ceremonie of prayer into the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and placing the houſe of Prayer ordinarily that way, and alſo placing the holy Table in the Eaſt end, and making that the Sanctuary. The whole Tabernacle and Temple ſtood in the mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt of the people of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But when they entred the Courts, the Court of Majeſtie in both places was in the <hi>Weſt.</hi> The Church is Gods throne in generall, as was the Temple &amp; Tabernac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Gods peopled well about it, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did, both in the Wilderneſſe, and the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> But the ſpeciall throne in the Church is the holy Table where we have our perfecteſt communion with God, It begins in Baptiſme, ends in the Lords Supper, and they are the beſt Saints that are admitted unto it, ſome reaſon there is of all that is ſaid from the diſtinction of times, The <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> before Chriſt by their looking into the <hi>Weſt</hi> profeſſed the darkneſſe of their dayes: we by looking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> profeſſe our times to be light.</p>
               <p>Its ſmall wiſdom to multiply needleſſe queſtions, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21240:39"/>as great wiſdome to anſwer them that be profitable, To ſatisfie the weak &amp; the wiſe alike is impoſſible, &amp; whiles one man cryes one thing, and ſome another, the greater part know not what they doe, or wherefore they come together.</p>
               <p>It hath often beene checked in Preachers to ſpeake of needleſſe matters, but ſhall that be needleſſe, which the times make neceſſary? let them aske no queſtions, &amp; raiſe no quarrels, with our Church and wee ſhall count it needleſſe to contend with them, that are convicted both of our faith and order, the only two things in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> greateſt joy, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.5. we ſhould be glad to preach no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but faith and the fruits of faith working by charity for ſalvation, but there is a neceſſitie to preach for order, when they that profeſſe to be children of our Church, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe appoſe her holy Orders. This my addition is not to purſue but pacifie the quarrell. Its my dutie to ſtand for the Church, and perſwade with all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to be of one minde and mouth.</p>
               <p>He that ſayes to mee, why is one place more holy then another? I may ſay to him, and why is one day more holy then another? Shall Saint <hi>Paul</hi> reſolve us in one word, upon one ground, for one end, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5, 6. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation makes the diſtinction, fulneſſe of knowledge muſt warrant it, and the glory of the Lord Ieſus muſt be the end of it. In Religion every day is alike to a Chriſtian that will not be a <hi>Iew,</hi> and one day is above another to a Chriſtian that will not be prophane, Hee that keeps no day to the Lord, gives him thanks that hee is not bound to keepe it, either as a <hi>Iew</hi> in <hi>yearely monethly,</hi> or <hi>weekly</hi> dayes, for the Apoſtle abſolves a Chriſtian from all dayes, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.16. and makes the obſervation of them to fruſtrate the Goſpel, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.10, 11.</p>
               <p>I ſay further, or to keepe it as a Chriſtian <hi>Iew,</hi> that is, to except as ſome doe the weekly Sabbath, and ſay by
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21240:40"/>Sabbath dayes, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. is meant yearly, but not of the weekly Sabbath, this is prejudice to Chriſtian Religion, that brings full freedome firſt to make all dayes alike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Chriſtian can make his choice of any day, There muſt in this point be a full abrogation of the law of days, before a Chriſtian be able to obſerve any other day to the Lord. Eſtimation of dayes with fulneſſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to the glory of Chriſt is firſt to keep no day againſt him, and then to keep any with thankfulneſſe for him that hath redeemed us from the bondage of the Law, Our dutie is to ſerve him, and our freedome to make choice of ſuch dayes as may be eſteemed to his glory, not only the Lords day in every weeke, but all other dayes eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Chriſtians above others to the honour of him whoſe ſervants they profeſſed themſelves. He that eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth one day above another may be a <hi>Iew,</hi> and obſtinate in his ignorance, yet a good Chriſtian that holds all dayes alike in the fulneſſe of perſwaſion, may likewiſe in the ſame hold one day above another, and give God glory in both, yea, greater then hee that is intangled ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to prophane a day that is lawfully commanded, or to be ſuperſtitious in keeping one of his owne will, and ſay it is commanded, when he cannot prove it but upon the ground of his own imagination.</p>
               <p>The fourth Commandement once commanded the ſeventh day in expreſſe words, but never the firſt in the like termes, it alwayes commandeth the duty of a holy day, and when all dayes are alike it ceaſeth not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the duties of a holiday, which are to be obſerved according to the determination which God hath left to the Chriſtian Church, which hath made the firſt day of the week above all other dayes, what adviſe he gave the Apoſtles to begin it, we read not, their example is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable upon two grounds. Firſt, becauſe Chriſt made all dayes alike, and therefore they had libertie to chooſe.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21240:40"/>Secondly, becauſe he made it lawfull to eſteeme one day above another, and the aſſignment hath been to the firſt day, and it were a ſinne either to denie the firſt as a <hi>Iew,</hi> or neglect the ſecond as a prophane perſon.</p>
               <p>I will conclude with the Apoſtle. Who, <hi>Gal,</hi> 4.10. in a full enumeration confirmes our point in hand, and takes away time as our Saviour takes away place, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.21, 22. for they are holy alike, and common alike, ſo that a man would admire what they meane that plead holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time, and implead holineſſe of place. If God be no where to be worſhipped, hee is to be worſhipped at no time, for the ſolemitie of the one inferres the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the other, and the nullitie of the one the nullitie of the other.</p>
               <p>Time and place are but elements of Religion, and in themſelves weake and beggarly, and commonly the weakeſt deſire them, and ſee not their bondage. God knowes how to begin the <hi>A B C,</hi> but hee likes not men ſhould learn no further. He compares time with time, and tels the <hi>Galath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ans</hi> that once they knew not God, but did as it were <hi>kindle their owne fires, and compaſſe themſelves about with their owne ſparkles, walke in the light of this fire, warmed themſelves by theſe ſpeaks,</hi> and for reward of their bad ſervice might have lyen downe in ſorrow. <hi>Eſay</hi> 50.11. But God in mercie altered their condition to know God, and that which is more to be knowne of God, in obeying the voice of Chriſt to receive light in him, to truſt in his Name, and ſtay upon him as their God. To this all other things are darkneſſe, and yet as Philoſophere teach us, <hi>non dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur purae tenebrae,</hi> there is no p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e darkneſſe without ſome mixture of light.</p>
               <p>Their ſervice and their ſeaſons wanted ſignification. Their ſervice unto them which by nature were no gods, teſtified of a duty done to an undue object, <hi>him whom
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21240:41"/>you ignorantly worſhip</hi> (ſaith Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Paul) I declare un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o you, Acts</hi> 17.23. Their ſeaſons were now out of reaſon, and eſpecially to mix themſelves with the <hi>Iews,</hi> and to obſerve their <hi>days,</hi> that is, their weekly Sabbath. <hi>Month<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that is, every new Moon. <hi>Times,</hi> that is, their three Feaſts of <hi>Eaſter, Pentecoſt;</hi> and <hi>Tabe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>macles. Yeares,</hi> that is, every ſeventh yeare, and the <hi>Iubile.</hi> And here Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> muſt be a guide unto us, leſt wee take hold of time, and turn it quite from God. <hi>Contra Adamant. Manich. cap.</hi> 15. <hi>Nos quoque &amp; dien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dominis um &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Paſcha ſoleuniter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e lebitam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; quaſli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alias Ghriſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas dierum feſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> quo pertione<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, non temporae obſervamus, ſed quaeillis ſignificantur tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: poribus.</hi> Wee keepe the Lords day and his Paſſeover ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely, and all other Chriſtian Feſtivals, but yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee obſerve not times, but the things ſignified i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we underſtand the ends to which they are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Chriſtians having libertie, uſe their time to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to whom they owe themſelves, and as the Apoſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> kept the Iewiſh Saboath, to gaine them by the opportunit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tie of the day. They kept alſo the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ordaiday in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous: equitie, to remember him that had redeemed them, and no man will deny that it is moſt equall that Ieſus Chriſt ſhould have ſuch a part of our time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Creation move us to yeeld him the laſt day in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Redemption will much move force <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> finde him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy of the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wedneſday</hi> and <hi>Friday</hi> are kept feſts, and the one is in memory of the treaſon of <hi>Iudas,</hi> which muſt be thought of, as ours, to humble us; for <hi>Iuda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> could never have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed Chriſt, it our fins had not done it, and we cannot remember this but with deteſtation of ourſelves, and grieve that wee have done wrong to the moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, as well as the moſt holy God. Aperpet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all faſt would never expiate the evill, yet to remember it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21240:41"/>wayes and by the day to keepe it in memory is a duty no godly man will deny, and his ſervice that day may well be the <hi>Letanie,</hi> as very fit in many paſſages to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the humble ſoule to lamentation. <hi>Friday</hi> is the memory of the curſe for our treaſon; no malediction had been upon our bleſſed Saviour, if wee had not laid it upon him, and ſinne, and Gods curſe, and all the cauſes of our lamentation, which as we muſt never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo there will be reaſon found why the Church chooſeth dayes to remember them.</p>
               <p>It is true that Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tels us, wee obſerve not times as <hi>Iewes,</hi> and put Religion and confidence in a day, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we had done a great worke, and deeply meritorious with God. But we know there ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as the Lords day to remember his Refurrection: Feſtivall dayes, to rejoyce in the triumphs of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; and ſet their examples before us as pat ternes of pietie. Faſts to humble our ſelves for our ſinnes, and Gods curſes vpon us, to feeke ſome ſpeciall bleſſing upon our ſelves, and ſuch Miniſters as the Church or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth for us, as the <hi>quatuor jejunia &amp;c.</hi> Indeed wee make Ceremonies of ſubſtance, and ſubſtance of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies. Some ſtand for a day, as if it were all their religion. Others abhorre their ſignification as ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and little uſe is made of any thing to give God due glory. I wiſh Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> words were well remembred that Chriſtians obſerve not times, but their godly ſignification and holy uſe; and ſo I end for time.</p>
               <p>The ſame libertie that is purchaſed for dayes, is alſo obtained for places. All places are alike to a Chriſtian, that is not a <hi>Iew,</hi> and one place is above another to a Chriſtian, that is not a profane perſon, and dare ſay the Church &amp; Table are common when Gods people are not in them. The Temple is a type of Chriſt, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21240:42"/>but one Temple. Chriſt is come and hath made all places alike, and he were a <hi>Iew</hi> that would defend either the Tabernacle of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or Temple of <hi>Salomon</hi> to take away his comming, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.21. Wee believe that the houre is come, that neither in Mount <hi>Gerizim</hi> nor Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> but every where God is to be ſerved, yet what place ſoever ſerves to record his name is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other common places, and holds the Ancient diſtinction of places in reſpect of the perſons meeting, to wit, the throne of Majeſtie, the place of Miniſtery, and the place of auditory.</p>
               <p>Neither let it ſeeme ſtrange that wee ſpeake of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> or of the <hi>Altar,</hi> for both are warrantable by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter authoritie, then can be brought by him that is ſet to appoſe <hi>Solomons Temple,</hi> as the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> before it had all the honour in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> ſo had the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Temples of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and both are worldly and beggerly rudiments of the times of darkneſſe, in compariſon of our times of light. A thing I could ſhew at large, but now I will limit my ſelfe to a few teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to declare. I ſpeak not without my betters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus l.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 724. ſayes that, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The moſt ancient Temples looked into the Weſt, and that a Chriſtian turning from ſuch Temples and their ſervice did <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. ſtand oppoſite to Idols, that is, with his face into the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> Hee firſt renounced the Idoll with his face into the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and then to ſignifie his converſion looked into the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. was taught to turn into the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> It is plain that confeſſion of Faith, and the prayers of Faith were with faces into the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. As light ſhines out of darkneſſe, &amp;c. A Pagan looked into the <hi>Weſt</hi> the place of darkneſſe, ſo did the <hi>Iew</hi> upon the ſame reaſon, though not with the ſame Religion. The
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21240:42"/>one is an Idolater, and confeſſeth blindneſſe, the other a true worſhipper, yet looking <hi>Weſtward</hi> for want of the Sunnes appearance, Satan is Gods Ape, and ſeeks in the Ceremony to abuſe God, yet may the <hi>Iew</hi> no more forſake the <hi>Weſt,</hi> then the Chriſtian the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> becauſe the Devill will be doing with both, Saint <hi>Hier. ad c.</hi> 6. <hi>Antor in myſteriis primum renunciamus eum qui in occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt, nobiſque moritur cum peccatis, &amp; ſic verſi ad eràeutem, pactu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> inimus cum Sole juſtitiae, &amp; ei nos ſervituros eſſe permittimus,</hi> In the myſteries, firſt we renounce him that is in the Weſt, and dies to us with ſinne, and ſo turning to the Eaſt, we enter a covenant with the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, and promiſe that will we ſerve him. <hi>Dyoniſ. l. de Eecleſ. Hier. c.</hi> 2. <hi>ad oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſuminverſus Satanam abjurabis, rurſuſque ad ortum te converteris Deum confiteberis,</hi> being turned to the <hi>Weſt,</hi> thou ſhalt abjure Satan, and againe converted to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> thou ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> acknowledge God, <hi>Ambr. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>De iis qui myſteriis initiantur, ad Orientem converteris, qui enim renuncia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diabolum ad Chriſtum convertitur, illum directa ceruit obtuitu, &amp;c.</hi> Thou art turned to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> for hee who renounceth the Devill is converted to Chriſt, and beholds him withdirect looke. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſeemes to me to allude to this cuſtome. <hi>Revel.</hi> 7.2. <hi>The Angell aſconds from the Eaſt,</hi> to meet and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them, that looke towards him, and ſeale them with the ſafe tie of the Sacrament by which Chriſtians ſeale their ſervice unto him.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls Baptiſme <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the very word uſed by Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſt.</hi> calls it <hi>regium characterem, Nazian.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> explains it to the ſenſe of Saint <hi>Iohn, Niſi ſignatus ſit ſuper te vultus Domini niſi characterem in te agnoſcat Angelus, quomodo pro te pugnabit, aut ab inimic is vindicabit. Nicet as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cholia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21240:43"/>quin per eum conſignuti cujuſnam Domini ſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, agnoſcimin, at que a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s; tuti conſervamur?</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eale, and the Angell brings it from the Eaſt, and at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> day the cuſtome is obſerved in the Church of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by the witneſſes for children that firſt looke in to the Weſt, and then into the Eaſt.</p>
               <p>For an <hi>Altar,</hi> foure arguments perſwade me in the Apoſtles words, to take it for the holy Table. <hi>Heb,</hi> 13.10. Firſt, it is that which Chriſtians have for their communion in oppoſidon to <hi>Iewer.</hi> Secondly, it is ſuch an <hi>Altar</hi> as we may <hi>be partakers of.</hi> Thirdly, this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a king muſt be by earing, in oppoſition to their eating. Fourthly; this eating is ſacramentall, and a ſigne of Chriſt exhibited as their<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was of Chriſt ſtill to be exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, and ſo the ſence is the ſame with <hi>partakers of a Table,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21. in oppoſition to a Pagan <hi>Altar,</hi> for the Apoſtle compares Table with Table, and Altar with Altar, and is indifferent in the appellation, as the Holy Ghoſt is elſwhere, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 41.22. <hi>Mal.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>This becauſe it is the ſigne of our greateſt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt, is alſo the chiefe ſigne of his preſence, and ſerves to ſet forth the place of Majeſtie, All men have communion with Chriſt in the reſt of his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. All may come to the word, be prayed for, but in this only the faithfull are admitted, novices to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, Penitents to be abſolved, and Petitioners not yet admitted, muſt all be gone when there comes the celebration of the Sacrament, and only the faithfull diſtinguiſhed from all the reſt, muſt draw neere to the holy Table, and take from it the holy Sacrament.</p>
               <p>Say not, why be not the Pulpit, Font, Deske, &amp;c. as holy, as the Table, you may receive a reaſon if you will from Gods more ſpeciall pretence, and our greateſt communion with Chriſt; Its the higheſt advancement a Chriſtian hath to be fed at Gods board, and with
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21240:43"/>Gods very bod y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and I ſee no error to conclude as I have done, that the holy Table is Gods Throne firſt to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Majeſtie, as being the Sanctuary and moſt holy place in the Church where it ſtandeth. It ſignifies like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his preſence with his people, that though they ſee him not, with their bodily eyes, yet they may be aſſured by their faith to finde him where hee fixeth his throne, Chriſt is not abſent from his Church, no needs he a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car to ſupply his place, but hee give us good aſſurance of his preſence and by many teſtimonies tels us he is with as, and in nothing form <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> really as in his holy Sacrament.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, for all the names of God they are alike to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, except he be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iew</hi> and hold one name more inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable then the reſt, and yet one narhe may be above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Chriſtian, excopt he will be prophane, and ſhew no reverence where hee hath the greateſt reaſon, firſt, from Chriſt himſelf that merit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a name, Secondly, from all creatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſhew it to be better then theirs. Thirdly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſelves, that have no name of, God that con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ins us and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> one; which is Ieſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Fourthly, in reſpect of God who is beſt knowne to us by this name.</p>
               <p>Firſt from merit, that Chriſt merits ſalvation for us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that hee merit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ought for himſelfe is denied by ſome, but in this the Scripture is more then mans au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Therfore becauſe he humbled himſelfe God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> him a name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. <hi>which he hath obtained</hi> as a Sonne, as a Saviour, as an heire, as a Redeemer, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Ye ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for ſuffering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with honour and glorie.</hi> That which I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſus merits alone that is his due, but he me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits honour at his Fathers hand, and therefore his Father will have us give it him, and reverence Ieſus above all names, and whoſoever denies it, does not his dutie, and to him. I leave him, that will not put up the injury of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21240:44"/>ſtiffe-knee, and untamed tongue, its merit, and therefore muſt be given to him, <hi>Thou art worthy to take the Booke and open the Seals, thou waſt killed and haſt redeemed us to God by thy bloud,</hi> Rev. 5.9. <hi>worthy is the Lambe that was ſlaine to receive power, riches, wiſdome, ſtrength, honour, glory,</hi> and bleſſing, <hi>Verſe</hi> 12. As God he hath this name by nature for <hi>who is the Saviour beſides the Lord,</hi> Chriſt hath by merit of his obedience title to glory and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of his name which are otherwiſe and without that of right belonging to him by the prerogative of his divine nature, and hypoſtaticall union, but by deſert of his humiliation, he hath merited, that his Deitie ſhould be acknowledged, nevertheleſſe for compunction with our nature, that as man he be adored with the honour of God, and his Name advanced above all names. As man he obtains it by grace, not the grace of adoption, but of perſonall union which is peculiar grace in Chriſt, for manhood cannot deſerve to be united to God, but it is of unſpeakable grace to grant ſuch a priviledge to our fleſh in the Sonne of God, as God and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, his vertues are meritorious, and his whole obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> both active and paſſive, a full purchaſe of redemption to us, and of glory to himſelfe, His exaltation is the fruit of his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, and the <hi>lifting up of his head, of his drinking of the breake in the way, Pſal.</hi> 110.7. Now a name were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without the honour, and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his name, <hi>in</hi> his name, or <hi>to</hi> his name it is due both in the ſubjection of the knee, and confeſſion of the tongue, and that of all, firſt, of thoſe that <hi>have righteouſneſſe and ſtrength in him</hi> to be ſaved, <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. Secondly, of them that are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed againſt</hi> him, and which at the day of judgement ſhall be aſhamed that they have been enemies to him and his in this world. <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.24. and made no uſe of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and death for them, who as their Lord redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing them and raiſing them, will be their judge, though
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21240:44"/>they would not have him their Saviour.</p>
               <p>This place is the originall text to which that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.11. and that other, <hi>Phil</hi> 2.10, 11. are branches, which are miſerably chopped and cut off from the true ſenſe to be ſet againſt our Churches Canon, which gives an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent reaſon for veneration at his name, took from the perfection of merit, and from this that all graces and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances are in him &amp; from him, &amp; no defect in him, but in our ſelves, if we be not ſaved, who therefore in naming his ſacred name <hi>Ieſus,</hi> is with all lowly reverence to be honoured in ſuch ceremony as ancient cuſtome, and the authoritie of our Church requires.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is from the names of all the creatures put together, which are not for excellency to be compared to this one name that the Sonne of God hath obtained. I know, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.4. the name Ieſus is not mentioned, and to avoid it our adverſaries will not have it ſo much as to be underſtood, becauſe all is ſaid of the ſonne, yet I am ſure the words immediatly preceding are for Ieſus hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and exalted, firſt, <hi>by himſelfe hee purgeth our ſinnes.</hi> Secondly, <hi>ſits downe on the right hand of the Majeſtie on high,</hi> his honour and humilitie go together, and the one is the cauſe of the other, Ieſus humbled is the cauſe of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus exalted, <hi>Ieſus crucified, Acts</hi> 2.36. is therefore made <hi>Lord and Chriſt,</hi> becauſe hee willingly for us ſuffered ſo great a reproach, and the two titles are not greater than the vertue meriting, and the name merited, as ſome have ſaid and written it upon their owne warrant, but they are as common attributes to a proper name, in which is the reaſon why they are given as dignities to it. Ieſus is therefore crucified, that he may be Lord of all, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as the anointed of God, in whom there is fulneſſe of redemption.</p>
               <p>The name that is better than Angels, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently above all creatures is to be worſhipped, but ſuch
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21240:45"/>is the name <hi>Ieſus</hi> given to the Sonne of God, wee need not feare a ſound for that is leſſe than Angels, and if it be Idolatry to worſhip them, then much more to adore a word, Ieſus is both the name and the thing, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9. <hi>A name above every name,</hi> of the creatures, and that ſerves ſufficiently for the force of this argument, that wee may worſhip the name <hi>Ieſus,</hi> if wee make it better than An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and therfore no Idolatry to reverence, bow, or bend <hi>in at</hi> or <hi>to</hi> the name, for we are not to ſeek evaſions in the varietie of the words uſed promiſcuouſly in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we may not take Gods name in vain, and the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of his name is the worſhip of it, for Gods name is himſelf, and to ſay, as ſome doe, I dare not, that reverence of Gods name, and adoration of it are not the ſame, It may be ſo in his Word and Ordinances, which I reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence but adore not, becauſe they are not God: but of his name and himſelfe I cannot ſo ſpeake, <hi>Eſay</hi> 42.8. <hi>I am the Lord, that is my name, and my glory I will not give to another, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His name, himſelfe and his glory are alike, and may be given to nothing leſſe than himſelfe, I ſpeak of the name Ieſus, not as given to ſome men by humane impoſition, but as given to our Redeemer by God, with a command of his adoration, and ſo I end my ſecond argument.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, from the benefit which is ours, wee never name our benefactors, but with great reverence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. Of all the names of God, this is above all names to us, for all other names containe God himſelfe as hee is againſt us, this only includes us, and our ſalvation in it, and therfore is given of God to us, ſo to think of it, and how can it be in our thoughts, above all other names, without reverence &amp; reſpect unto it, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. as there is ſalvation in no other perſon, ſo there is no other name to expreſſe it, and therefore wee may well make our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of reverence at the mention of it.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:21240:45"/>
               <p>Laſtly, from God himſelfe made known unto us, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> 6.3. As hee reveals himſelfe, ſo are wee to worſhip him, and as he does this by one name more than another, ſo may we acknowledge it without offence. Now of all names none more expreſſive of Gods goodneſſe unto us, than this name Ieſus, and therefore we eſteeme it, of all the names of God moſt precious, and in which he is moſt delighted to be worſhipped, to confeſſe, <hi>that Ieſus is the Lord, Phil.</hi> 2.11. is a glory to Chriſt, but the text ſayes it is to the glory of God the Father; &amp; therfore no wrong done to one perſon, when wee performe worſhip in the name of an other.</p>
               <p>Shortly,
<table>
                     <head>In Religion</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>All dayes are alike,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>one day is above another.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>All places are alike,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>one place is above another.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>All names are alike,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>one name is above another.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>There is no contradiction nor oppoſition to Gods Word, when all dayes are alike, to make one day above another, when all places are alike to preferre one place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another, when all names are alike to advance one name before another, Eſtimation begins the difference, and where it puts none againſt God, it may ſet up one for God, Eſtimation muſt be grounded upon knowledge that we be not ignorant in our thoughts, and all muſt be to the glory of him who hath purchaſed our liberty from the bondage of the one, and granted us freedome in the other, to make our choice of ſuch circumſtances as may advance and advantage our Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.3. in <hi>Timothie</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> teach us wiſdome how to walke with the wiſe, and yet to the wicked to <hi>give no place by ſubjection for an houre,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21240:46"/>
                  <hi>the truth of the Gospel.</hi> Emiſſaries and Spies in the Church muſt be avoided, and it was Saint <hi>Peters</hi> great fault, ὀυκ ὀρθοποδεῖν, to give offence in ſeeking to avoid it, and his feare to offend was his greateſt offence, and that which is moſt to be lamented, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, his hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie is the cauſe of others diſſembling with him, and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> companion is corrupted in this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill concord, and the Apoſtle left alone to vindicate the truth of the Goſpel. Hee that went furtheſt in the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and circumſtance of Religion, is the ſtricteſt and ſtouteſt to ſtand for the ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>A good pattern for our dayes of peaceable proceedings in the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.21. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is accuſed not to live after the Church cuſtomes, adviſed to ſhew the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation to be falſe, &amp; to ſubmit with foure men to purifie himſelfe, and be at the charges of ſhaving for a <hi>Nazarite,</hi> and although he vowed not with the foure men, yet hee had not avoided that vow, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.18. and now readily to give ſatisfaction undergoes the whole counſell of his brethren and although the event proved not ſucceſſefull: yet was it ſufficient to ſhew his care to be at the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches command to the utmoſt, not to offend any zealous of the Law, eſpecially beleeving, and in whom there was hope to be reclaymed from holding <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt Chriſt. Would God this moderation were in our times, and that people could diſcerne betweene circumſtances and ſubſtence in true Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iude, Verſe</hi> 23. <hi>hate the garment ſpotted with the fleſh,</hi> is ſtrangely taken by ſome, and compared to a ſhadow, when it includes a mayn ſubſtance as fire to devoure, and out of which, nothing can ſave but quicke pulling out. <hi>Creepers</hi> into houſes, <hi>Verſe</hi> 4. <hi>murmurers</hi> and <hi>complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> of their Governours are compared to a leprous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious garment, which we muſt flie as the Plague. I ſee no ſuch peſtilence in a Surpleſſe as in theſe, from which
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21240:46"/>
                  <hi>Good Lord, deliver us,</hi> and let every good man pull away his neighbour from pinning himſelfe upon their ſleeves, that ſlily creepe into corners to ſeduce men from our Church, and let all learne to lay this text more againſt an Hereticke and a Schiſmaticke, than a Ceremonie of the Church; for certainly the ſenſe is more in that, than in this.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Abſtain from all appearance of evill,</hi> is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other proofe againſt Ceremonies, and yet it is cleere, the Apoſtle means it of prophecie. Firſt, we muſt not deſpiſe it, if we mean not to <hi>quench the ſpirit.</hi> Secondly, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie muſt be tried. Thirdly, what is good muſt be held. Fourthly, that which is evill, the very appearance of it muſt be avoided. This is ill applied to Ceremonies; for it is not the evill appearance of every thing we muſt abſtain from: for then we ſhould hold nothing that is good, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the beſt things; for commonly they moſt offend, and finde ſenſe an ill judge of them: but here again, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, take heed not onely of evill doctrines, but their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appearance. Or if any will have the words generall, they muſt be applyed to that which is evill, and that by a gradation. Evill muſt be avoided, not onely in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: but the very circumſtances, wee muſt not admit the leaſt of evils, and therfore the thing muſt be evill that we avoid. To ſay it may appeare, ſo to be, is not enough; for what will not ſome with their wits work into ill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, and make the people like bird-eyed-horſes ſtart at any thing. Let men be ſolid, and not ſuperficiall. Studie to be ſerious, and not verball, in ſetting falſe faces upon things.</p>
               <p>I have done, and muſt adde my concluſion from the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and wiſh wee may ſee the times ſet forth in theſe words, <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.1. <hi>How beautifull are thy goings with ſhooes, O Princes daughter; the joynts of thy thighes are like jewels: the work of the hand of a cunning work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:21240:47"/>O God, thou art the cunning workman, and onely able to ſet our joynts like jewels, and make our thighes ſtable, and the very wheel-bones (for ſo the word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies in the articulation) ready to holy motions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions to thy ſelfe, and then I am ſure wee ſhall have our feet ſhod, and not walke barefoot upon theſe ſharpe ſtones, and ſcruples daily caſt in amongſt us. Wee have thy Goſpel of peace, ſhooe our feet with the preparation of it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.15. and put an end to theſe miſerable wars amongſt us. Thou that giveſt us the fignes of thy preſence, preſerve us in thy truth. Let thy Miniſters be clothed with holineſſe, and thy people rejoyce in thy ſalvation. Let the bleſſed Angels pitch their tents about us, and watch for us, They are thine honorable atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, let them be from thee to us as our <hi>Corps-du-guarde,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:21240:47"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
